Okay. Um, good morning. We are live.
So, today is a special day because this
is a day when we meet God
and we are now in the last four kantos
um 31 32 33 and we are in the imperium
which is a seat of God.
Um,
so we'll be doing a lot today, but I
just want to first make sure there are
no questions, issues from the previous
four days. Are there any questions you
have about
uh what what we've learned so far?
Anyone?
Yes.
>> Um, so I remember last time we were
talking about how the angels existence
are really not that admirable like you
don't want to be an angel. But uh when I
went back and when I read the part about
describing angels, I think Dante was uh
actually trying to be a little bit
tongue and cheek here. Like he was
trying to say that it's not great to be
an angel without saying that being
without explicitly saying that being an
angel is not that desirable. Is that is
that what he's trying to do?
>> Yeah. So the thing about design comedy
that's very important to appreciate is
that it's all very subtle. Um and
there's a really important reason for
the subtlety. So how so do you guys know
how people learn divine comedy or how
they transmitted divine comedy back then
for hund hundreds of years? Like if you
were in school and we had to learn
divine comedy, how would we learn it?
So according to what I remember like the
teacher will have one book and he would
he would read it uh and he would read on
the podium and you listen and you copied
it down
>> and then what would you do?
You you memorized it. Do you understand?
Okay. So remember how before we said
that divine comedy is meant to be read
aloud and and listened to was also meant
to be memorized. And what's happening is
that divine comedy is designed to expand
your imagination.
And obviously as you memorize divine
comedy, it's like Shakespeare, right? If
you memorize Shakespeare, your fluidity
in English language increases, but so
does your imagination.
And what increases the imagination is
the subtlety embedded within divine
harmony because you actually don't know
what you memorized. But over time
because it is implanted in your brain
almost as an operating software the more
experiences you have uh the more
questions you have the poem expands in
your imagination it's infinite
um and then it drives you into um
greater imagination yourself and that's
why I say that divine harmony is really
the basis of the uh renaissance because
you just look at any renaissance
uh painting you can trace it back to the
to a line or a tursid in the vine comedy
right and what's what's happened is that
line has expanded itself inside
uh the brain and it's almost like seeds
taking root and just growing into into
trees and and so that's um that's what
the effect of divine comedy is um and it
works because of paradox and sility if
it's too blatant it's if it's too in
your face then your mind doesn't focus
it on as much. Okay? But because it's so
subtle, you you feel as though there's
some stuff I have not yet discovered,
right? It's like a puzzle you're trying
to assemble together. Your brain keep on
working subconsciously on it for like 40
50 years. And and that's really the
power of divine comedy. And that's why
it's really hard for people to express
the impact of divine harmony because it
works at a subconscious level. And this
is what Cory Young would would call
refer to as the collective unconscious.
Okay? It's really the very basis of our
journey. Look, the reality, look, if you
think about it, the reason why we're
able to sit down together and have these
very rich discussions about the um
divine comedy. Uh what enables
this discussion
is the fact that Donnie credited
modernity itself, right? the idea of
individuality, create the idea of
debate, uh, dialogue. Okay. So, we are
living in Donniey's world and we all
basically have minds that are shaped by
by Donnie himself. All right. Does that
make sense? Okay. Any more questions
before we continue before we begin?
All right. So, now what I want to do is
I want to look at a comment from YouTube
that I found very interesting. Okay. And
it's it's from YouTube. It's just a
comment. It's a very long comment. So,
here it is. Um, uh, Carol, could you
give me a favor and and read the
comment?
And, and this goes back to, um,
discussion from last class, which is the
coin. What's the coin doing in in
heaven? What is its purpose? Right? The
coin is meant to be a metaphor for
faith, but that doesn't really make
sense because the coin represents
something material. But and and this
person um has a very interesting
explanation. Okay. Can you read um
Carol?
>> Yeah. In Pariso cont 24 right at line
number 24. Beatatric officially hands
Dante over to St. Peter to initiate the
examination. In Alan Mandelbal's
translation that exact line reads, "And
tests him as you please on matter's
grave. Dante deliberately places the
word tested at line 24 inside KTO 24
inside the sphere of the 24 elders the
traditional symbol of the codified
closed scriptural cannon. He is
screaming to the reader that he's
stepping into an institutional trap.
This directly mirrors the structural
constraints found in the original four
gospels. The Peter paradigm. The entire
miracle of the coin in the fish's mouth
begins precisely at verse 24. Here the
establishment corners Peter to demand an
institutional tax. Dante mirrors this
textually. The exact disciple who
watched Jesus bypass human currency by
extracting it from nature is transformed
in Kanto 24 into the ultimate papal
gatekeeper demanding a standardized
church coin from Dante's purse. The
interrogation blueprint. This verse
establishes the scriptural precedent for
institutional authorities demanding
official credentials from a wild
spiritual force, stating that the
Pharisees questioned him. Dante uses his
own line 24 to step into this exact
role. Submitting to Peter's
interrogation on paper to satisfy the
religious empire. the illusion of the
purse. Here Jesus stuns the disciple by
declaring how difficult it is for those
relying on physical coins and
institutional currency to enter the
kingdom. Dante plays on this irony by
using purse imagery to satisfy Peter
knowing full well that in the infernal
purses are the exact symbols used to
damn corrupt popes. the trap of power.
At the last supper, a dispute arises
among the disciples as to which of them
was considered to be the greatest. The
disciples were were already craving an
earthly hierarchy. By looking at the
textual architecture of the comedy, we
can see Dante play was playing a master
level game. He knew that physical
institutions and dogmatic checklists
were destined to crumble. By using the
stamped coin at line 24, Dante wasn't
blindly submitting to church church
dogma. He was using the empire's own
currency to smuggle his formless cosmic
fire past the medieval gatekeepers.
>> Okay. Yeah. So this is brilliant. Okay.
And it shows you the level of complexity
of the divine comedy. All right. So let
me make certain points. Point number one
is last class we appreciated how the
literary analysis of divine common how
how deep it is at a literary level and
you can only understand that if you
understand the Italian right um here
this person is pointing out to the
numerology
of the divine comedy the numerological
structure of it 24 you may not know this
but 24 is a very important number for a
variety of reasons but
doesn't just refer to a Bible. What it
really is referring to is the classic
epic poems of the world at this time
which are Homer, the Iliad, the Odyssey
and Inads and and Virgil's Iniad. These
are all written in 24 books. Okay? So 24
is almost like a divine mystical number
at this point. So that's why it's
important. Um so the numerology is
something that you can spend decades
examining and obviously um he's doing
that. Second point is how subversive
divine comedy is. The point so we look
at divine comedy at a pretty simplistic
level but if you just go line by line
you can see how divine comedy is
constantly subverting itself. How your
interpretation is breaking down if you
do more and more analysis. And that's
intentional. And the reason why he does
that is to make Divine Comedy infinite
universe where you can go back and
explore um uh uh forever. And the third
point um that's very important to
appreciate is that ultimately what Dante
wants is for us to always question
authority, right? to question not just
Peter to not only question uh the church
but to also question Dante and
ultimately to question ourselves to
create a constant almost an infinite
process of self- inquiry self-debate and
self-discovery
and that's why you can spend your entire
life just reading my comedy at multiple
uh angles and it's never never enough so
the ultimate goal of our seminar is just
to introduce you divine comedy. Do not
believe
that this is that like I'm giving you
the final interpretation. Okay, that
that's silly. This comment shows you how
complicated uh the divine comedy is.
Okay, but I'm providing you a framework
in order for you to engage your own
process of self-creation, self-discovery
when you journey into the vine comedy,
right? Because once once you have the
framework allows you to better
understand and journey through the mind
comedy but once but but then as you
journey some more you will break down
this framework and create your own
framework. Okay. This is a process that
um Harold Bloom the great Yale literary
scholar refers to as um as
um creative self-destruction. Okay.
>> Right. Uh yes. So after you read the
question, you read the comment about uh
St. Peter, I'm actually inspired to ask
a question. So yesterday we talked about
how uh Peter was pointing at the Vatican
on earth and he was going, "Ah, these
guys are nasty." Uh but Peter here
himself by asking uh Dante the pilgrim
about the coin is also complicit in what
the church is doing. So what what point
is Dante trying to make here? Is he
trying to say that St. Peter is
criticizing the church. Is he trying to
say that St. Peter is the church? Or is
he saying that St. Peter is a mix of the
two?
>> Okay. What makes Dante um very hard for
people to understand is at the heart of
Dante is
his democratic spirit. Okay. He is
absolutely
anti- power, anti- hierarchy, anti-
status.
Right? So the idea that after Jesus died
uh Peter will then become the first
pope. Dante finds this um perverting
Jesus' legacy because Jesus came to our
world um and sacrifice himself in order
to free us to free to liberate us from
power itself. Right? And then for Peter
to say, well, I was closest to Jesus
because remember after he died, the
apostles fought over his legacy. Um,
finally felt this is a perversion of the
message of Jesus. Okay, the message of
Jesus is that there's divinity within us
and we look into us, we can liberate
ourselves. We don't need God. We don't
need hierarchy. We don't need the church
anymore. Okay, that was the ultimate
message of Jesus. and and that and
that's what Don is trying to do in
divine comedy as well, right?
>> Um I learned from a Yale scholar. Great
question, Renee. Um so um I was looking
back at um Yale professor Mazafa's um
interpretation of this Kanto and um
there are tons of paradoxes um including
the coin. And so on verse 38 um at 37 38
of kantha 24 do test this man concerning
the faith by which you walked upon the
sea. Ask him points light and grave da
da da da da. So um I don't know if you
remember from the bible that um Peter
was actually quite doubtful when Jesus
asked him to walk upon the sea. He
actually didn't have sufficient faith
until you know Jesus is like why aren't
you going there? Um and and then he
ended up doing that. But I think um it's
also very human.
It's also very human. Um and and and I
think that's one of the paradoxes things
>> and and it's ironic that Peter is the
one who asked about faith because if you
read the gospels, Peter is the one who
has the least faith in Jesus, right? And
that's what Jesus tells Peter. And uh so
so there's so much irony uh uh embedded
in the vine comedy. Okay. Um any more
comments or questions before we move on?
Okay. So something really interesting
happened yesterday while you guys are on
break and one of you wrote a poem. Okay.
And I don't want to put you in you on
the spot, but uh um I asked for
permission and we're going to read the
poem uh together. Okay. So, can you come
please and and help us read read read
the poem? Well, first of all, introduce
yourself and tell us the background as
to how you came to write this poem.
>> Yeah, my name is uh Jay. Um uh how I
came to write this poem. I had some time
to kill in my hotel room yesterday and
um I uh you know, obviously being away
from family, it's it's uh and you know,
it's Father's Day weekend, it's kind of
difficult. So um you know decided to
make something in the spirit of Dante in
the spirit of hope uh for you know for
my kids. Yeah. So that's where this
comes from.
>> Okay. So can you just read us a poem
>> tonight or uh
far in the glass room? No huang no
hunching rain.
No hunching rain on the stones. No
green.
Just quiet.
Sorry.
Just quiet
and a week in the in the old poets's
country of light. Learning the sea
between us.
Sorry,
nervous. Uh, learning the sea between us
is a
is a sorry
is a um what was that?
Sorry, I couldn't read my own writing.
Okay,
>> it's a trick we keep playing. Uh the
souls that looks look scattered each
each one on its own not split at all.
One light the other young hila. This is
in the lay too. So So you are you are
near though the south seas between us.
Glass rooms far light and still the
jalan pulan.
And love the poet says moves the sun and
stars and binds the loose pages of life
into one.
From a hawken mountain to green water.
The long climb came only to stand up in
you. Uh, three of you each holding a
different measure. None holding half,
each of you home. The way a man once
crossed this dark sea to his son with
nothing to give but I see you climb
Jangan.
That's all. That's all
from the far edge of of it all. um as we
turn through the dark up the long climb
hope.
>> Great. Thank you so much. That that was
beautiful. Okay. All right.
So, um can you tell us what the poem is
about?
>> Um it's about for me it's about um um
being away and I'm trying to convey uh
to my kids why I'm away and uh
yeah. Okay. So you see what's happened
is that he could only write this poem
because of his love for his children,
right? This this cosmic connection with
his children. And that's why we need to
recognize that for Dante, Beatatrice is
a real person. Okay? We know
historically they didn't know each other
that that well. They met when when they
were eight or nine, spent a few years
together, then they they They went
apart. They they were apart and then
Beatus died when she was like 24. Okay.
So the time they actually spent together
was not that much. But when we divine
comedy, she comes across as a real
person.
>> And for Donna, she was a real person. Uh
she was in con constant communication
with her soul. It is possible to do this
like where you're not even together may
she she may not even be alive. She she
was not alive. But with your
imagination, with your love, you can be
in communication with her across
dimensions. Okay? And that's what drives
the poetry. All right? That's why love
has to be between two people. It can't
be between you and God. It can't be
between between you and money or
anything material. It has to be between
two people.
Okay? and and uh you focus your love in
a way and at the person your imagination
just explodes. Okay, that's what drives
your imagination. All right, so this is
a testament to that. So thank you very
much.
Okay. So, we are now in heaven. And when
we're in heaven, there's a problem
because in heaven, there's no time and
space. Which means that you can't
actually perceive anything. Okay. But if
you can't perceive, what's the only way
that you can see? Then
you can't perceive.
Excuse me.
>> Imagine. No, you don't. No, not not the
imagination, right? What?
>> Um, you can use your spiritual spidey
senses.
>> Okay. Well, there's actually a word for
spiritual spidey sense. It's called
what? H
>> intuition or what?
>> Uh, well, what's behind your intuition?
Come on, guys. Like your your your
intuition, your spidey sense. What do we
call that?
How how do you see if you can't see?
>> You feel.
>> Yeah. Exactly. Thank you. Yes. Your
emotions, right? Okay. This this is this
is why it's important not to go to
school because then you can actually,
you know, use use your intuition, your
emotion. It's your emotions. Okay. So,
in other words, when he goes to heaven,
he can't actually see anything but
because it's so blinding. It's so
beautiful. Okay. But he can feel it. And
so what he's trying to do is convey uh
heaven to us through his poetry. And um
so what heaven is is our happiest
moment. It is pure bliss, pure joy, pure
happiness. Okay. So to start the class,
I want us to think of our happiest
memory. A memory that brings constant
delight to us as we think more and more
about it. And then that helps us better
understand the architecture of heaven.
Okay. So I'm gonna write this down. All
right. And like again uh I just want
happy memories. Your happiest memory.
Okay. Anyone?
Yes.
>> Uh I remember that one time when I was
Okay, this sounds silly, but I was in
primary school and the teacher was about
to punish someone unjustly for something
that he wasn't really at fault for
doing. And I stood up to the teacher and
I told her that's that's stupid. And
everyone in the class cheered for me and
in the end the guy didn't get punished.
>> Okay.
>> Yes. That's a great memory. Yes. Thank
you. Right. Your selfless generosity.
Okay. Selfless sacrifice.
>> That's rewarded.
Okay.
All right. That's one good memory. Yes.
That's a great memory by the way.
Beautiful. Yes.
Yes. Uh I remember when I was first time
in New York I I think everything is new,
everything is different. This is a
different world is quite different from
China. So that make really make me feel
shocked and make me feel amazed and uh
yeah.
>> Wait. Right. So novelty.
Okay. Novelty,
surprise,
shock.
>> Yes. What else?
Yes. For me, it was um after the IB
exams, I finally got to sleep for 12
hours and when I woke up, it was the
happiest feeling I've ever felt.
>> Okay, we call this relief and release,
right? Relieve and release. So, the idea
is,
you know, for quite a few months you
were nervous and all this tension built
up in in you, right? And then you were
able to release it. Good. What else?
Yes. Um, so I would like to share my
experience of getting my my dog because
it was really special for me. I had been
like basically begging my parents to
have a dog for such a long time and we
were going to adopt but there were
always always things in the way so we
couldn't get a dog and finally I did um
during my first year in middle school
and that was really my happiest memory.
I'm so glad that I have my dog right
now.
>> Great. Yeah. So it's idea of wish
fulfillment, right? You have a wish.
This is something that you always wanted
and it fulfills itself. So wish
fulfillment. Good. What else? Uh yes.
>> To return home after a year of studying
abroad and stuff. Like the minute I hit
the airport, I'm like, "Yeah, I'm back."
>> Exactly. Right. Returning home, right?
I would say
returning home. Yeah. Exactly.
What else? Yes. Uh when I first met my
um jazz piano hero for the first time uh
in his live show, I was transcended with
this art.
>> Okay. Right. So um
um so there there's a concept called
flow,
right? Which is intense
focus or devotion to your passion. Okay.
Yes. So flow. Yes. Yes.
If I may, I think this count counts
inside of really being in the flow, but
especially um I'm really into
mathematics and when I understand a
really difficult mathematics concept, I
feel really happy and because I have a
lot of friends around me that I can
really talk talk about this kind of
stuff with them. Um it makes me feel uh
makes me feel very good that I'm
actually able to understand all of this
and be able to talk to people about it
that really understand what I
>> yeah I wouldn't say this is flow I would
say this is more like self creation okay
or self-discovery
right when you discover something new
about the world and share with others
okay but but what what makes it really I
think happy for you is the sharing
aspect right you've you've discovered
something new and share some other
people that helps them learn more.
Right. So, it's really a sharing of the
knowledge, right? Sharing knowledge.
Good.
Right.
Yes. Anyone else?
>> I'm curious about what's your happiest
memory?
>> Well, well, obviously my my children.
Yeah. When I'm when I'm with my
children. Yes. Anyone else? Yes.
I remember like back then um I met this
girl online and I just I just and I feel
like um like my soul is in ecstasy and
my soul funos and back then we we we
didn't even met each other yet, right?
And but just knowing that uh there's a
such existence another human being that
is so imaginative and um so poetic and
it makes me like like like for for
several days I feel like I'm a
psychedatic you know
>> so I understand thank you okay this is a
connection right
>> connection
right or we can also say community
all right yes thank Thank you. Anyone
else?
Yes.
>> I I was uh born and raised in a culture
uh where uh you know it's this uh felio
duty for um for somebody to study really
hard to make uh achievement in in in in
his life and to bring honor to the
family and to the neighborhood and to
the community. So I felt most uh uh
excited and most happy when I won those
uh you know awards and uh in those
competitions
uh in my hometown and bring honor to my
family and my school and the whole city.
So uh I couldn't imagine something even
greater than that. So for me it's uh to
be in the right community and to be
supported and to to lead that community
and to bring honor to that community.
>> Great. Yeah. So this we will call this
recognition and validation, right? You
are recognized for your achievements and
you're validated for them. Good. Okay.
Great. This is a lot. Anyone else?
Okay.
Like sometime in art museum I can
experience kind of transcendental and
mysterious uh aesthetic experience.
>> Yeah. Beauty, right? When you get
something beautiful, you are very happy.
Okay. So, yeah, we can keep on going.
Okay. But you you get the sense of what
happiness is, right? And what heaven is
is just every second there's just
continuous happiness, right? So just
think of your happiest moment and then
um um just think that this goes on
forever. Okay? So that's what that's
what heaven is. All right. Let me ask
you a question. Let me now ask you a
question.
Are there any songs or poems or artwork
that triggers your happiness?
Okay. Like what are they?
>> Yes.
>> Uh hypers specific but uh medieval
illuminated manuscripts.
>> Okay. Sure. Okay.
Manuscripts. Okay.
Sure. Okay. What else?
Yes.
>> Uh, I would say house music.
>> House music. Okay. All right.
Yes.
>> I like to say some like really classical
music like really in the middle ages but
maybe not that really.
>> Yeah.
>> What else?
>> For me is a novel and It has really
beautiful pros and it's it it the the
words are used in a way that are so
unique and creative that it it shocks
you.
>> Good. Okay. So guys, it's going to be
music. Okay. Music is a thing that's
going to trigger your happiest memories
and pro probably also your other
memories as well. But so that's what
Donn is going to do. He's going to
construct because he does he doesn't
remember anything. Okay, Don is going to
keep on saying about this how he goes to
the imperium and he's going to meet God.
He doesn't remember anything because it
is so blinding because it is so beyond
time and space. Okay. But what he has is
the is the emotions with it and from
these emotions he's going to reconstruct
reimagine his experience in Imperium in
a way that we can appreciate. and he's
going to design the poem with the music
in a way that triggers our happiest
memories so that we can experience with
him uh the imperium. Okay. Does that
make sense? Okay. All right. So, we now
move towards
panto
uh 30 the imperium. Okay. again. We saw
the angels.
Uh we've we've journeying a long way
through the cosmos and now we are
finally in the imperium.
Um and again what is paradoxical about
heaven is that there is in fact a
hierarchy, right? Just because you go to
heaven doesn't mean that you've
succeeded because there are some really
dumb kids in heaven, okay? like Picarda.
Um, and the hierarchy of the of the
heavens also suggests that there are
certain things that that you have to
doubt. For example, why is Peter, right?
Um, why is he outside the empirium,
right? That that makes you question a
lot of things he says. So again, there's
so much subtlety, there's so much
nuance, there's so much paradox to the
mind comedy. It forces in you into a
lifetime of self inquiry. Okay. All
right. So, so let's read read um
Paradise 30.
>> KTO 30.
Perhaps 6,000 miles away from us. The
sixth hour burns. And now our world's
inclines shadowed to an almost level
bed. So that the span of heaven high
above begins to alter so that some stars
are no longer to be seen from our deep
earth. And as the brightest handmade of
the sun advances, heaven shuts off. One
by one its lights until the lovely
loveliest is gone. So did the triumph
that forever plays around the point that
overcame me point that seems enclosed by
that which it encloses.
>> Uh the point of course refers to God.
Okay. And what's really important to
understand is like God is both being and
becoming. Okay. So God is the source the
big bang but also God is the perimeter
okay of the universe right and how do we
expand the perimeter of the universe
the imagination do you understand okay
so we humans and this is what's really
um shocking about Donnie is that he's
saying that we humans participate in the
creation process ourselves whenever we
use our imagination and what he's going
to say that's even more controversial is
that only we can do this. Okay? Not the
angels, not God, nothing else but
humans. Okay? All right. Uh, keep on
going.
Fade gradually from my sight, so that my
seeing nothing else, and love compelled
my eyes to turn again to Beatress.
If that which has been said of her so
far were all contained within a single
praise, it would be much too scant to
serve me now. The loveliness I saw
surpassed not only our human measure,
and I think that surely only its maker
can enjoy fully. I yield. I'm defeated
at this passage more than a comic or
tragic poet has ever been by a barrier
in his theme. For like the sun that
strikes the frailst eyes, so does the
memory of her sweet smile deprive me of
the use of my mind. From that first day
when in this life I saw her face until I
had this vision. No thing ever cut the
sequence of my song. But now I must
assist from this pursuit in verses of
her loveliness just as each artist who
has reached his limit must.
>> Okay. So Beatrice and Dante have reached
the imperium. This is Journey's end.
And it is Bonnie's love for Beatatrice
that has carried him so far up into the
cosmos.
Um, and
being here, what does he want to do
above all else?
What does he want to do?
This is Dante, right?
>> Anyone
>> describe Beatatrice or is that what he
wants to do?
>> He wants to write poetry to Beatress,
right? Do you understand? For him, your
fullest expression of your love someone
is to use your imagination
to express the poetry. Because what?
Because why would you want to do that?
Why would you want to write the poetry?
>> Because you can't help but to express
how much love you have for this person
or how awesome, wonderful this person
is.
>> Right? So poetry is the highest
expression of your love for someone. But
why is that the case? Yes. to connect to
unify with those who you love
to connect with those who you love and
also to show your love and brings others
into this love as well. You understand?
That's what poetry is doing. Yeah. Yeah.
Of course
>> it immortalizes love. Um kind of like
the Shakespearean sus.
>> That's right. Right. To share your love
across time and space.
Okay. So that's what he wants to do.
What's his problem?
It's a problem. What? What's the
problem? He spent his entire life
writing love poetry to Beatrice in order
to immortalize her. In order immortalize
her love, their love. But what's the
problem now?
>> Um, I'm not sure his wife is okay with
this. But he has a wife.
[laughter]
What
>> uh you know uh I I got a wife. I I I
know wife is kind of responsibility but
not love. You know I'm sorry to tell her
that.
>> How many people know that love is not
for a wife but you know the love is
something that you cannot you cannot you
cannot touch. You really want it but you
cannot touch. That is love. You can
touch it. This is not love. This is kind
of responsibility and have to pay
everything for her. My my point being
that uh ideally you want to marry
someone you love and if you break the
vows of marriage which by the way you
made to God because you met your
soulmate then you're also betraying God
in the process.
Okay, I'm sorry. [laughter] Um, okay.
Ideally, okay, but in the real world,
there are things such as class
hierarchies. There are lots of
constraints, right? So, appar So, um,
Beatric and Donnie came from different
class backgrounds. And in this culture,
all marriages are arranged, right?
There's no dating market. It's like you
don't go online and says, "Hm, I'm going
to look for, you know, my deal." That
doesn't No, no. It's like you're
assigned someone to marry. And so in
this in this culture, marriage and love
are not the same thing. Marriage is just
for convenience. Um and love is the
expression of beauty and truth. Okay.
All right.
Okay. So the question is what's the
problem here? He wants to write a poem
to Beatatric. He wants to write a verse.
But there's a problem. What's the
problem? I I mean in in the poem he he
does say right I must desist from this
pursuit in verses of her loveliness just
as each artist has rejected he's he's
reached his limit.
>> Yeah. But why is it has he reach his
limit?
>> She's heavenly and he's earthly and he
can't like fully express how good she
is. He ran out of words for it maybe.
>> Okay. Well that's true. But it's not
because he's earthly and she's heavenly,
right? It's because in their ascent
Beatrice has become more beautiful over
time,
right? And so once we reach this point,
he now has reached the limit of his
imagination. He's now reached the limit
of his poetry. Okay? Right? So there's a
limit here.
Um,
why should we not believe him?
Why should we not believe him?
>> Because there's no real like limitation
for the imagination.
>> Exactly. First of all, there's no
limitation. Also, he's not modest, man.
Donnie is not a modest guy. If he's he's
telling you, oh, you know what? I can't
really do this. He's he's trying to
trick you into something. Okay. So So
this is a paradox. All right. Uh let's
keep on reading. Um Carol
verse
verse 34.
So she in beauty as I leave her to a
herald that is greater than my trumpet
which nears the end of its heart theme
with voice and bearing of a guide whose
work is done. began again from matter's
largest sphere. We now have reached the
heaven of pure light, light of the
intellect, light filled with love, love
of true good, love filled with
happiness, a happiness surpassing every
sweetness. Here you will see both ranks
of paradise and see one of them wearing
the same aspect which you will see again
at judgment day.
>> Okay, so here it would be very nice to
have the Italian, okay? and to be read
aloud in Italian because I think with
these words
um this marks a very distinct
um use of language and light of the
intellect, light filled with love, love
of true good, love filled with
happiness, a happiness surpassing every
sweetness. It's like a song. Okay, it's
a very um lyrical song that conjures up
our our best memories. Okay. Again, we
don't have the Italian, but if we did, I
think that's what that that's what would
happen. Okay. It's it's like the highest
possible
um vibration. Okay. It's very light,
very lovely, pure joy. So, imagine
angels singing. Okay. This poetry is
really angels singing together. Okay. Um
keep on going.
>> Verse
46.
>> Yeah. 46.
like sudden lightning scattering the
spirits of sight so that the eye is then
too weak to act on other things it would
perceive. Such was the living light
encircling me leaving me so enveloped by
its veil of radiance that I could see no
thing. The love that calms this heaven
always welcomes into itself such a
salutation to make the candle ready for
its flame. No sooner had these few words
entered me then, I became aware that I
was rising beyond the power that was
mine, and such new vision kindled me
again, that even the purest light would
not have been so bright as to defeat my
eyes, deny my sight. And I saw light
that took a river's form, light flashing
reddish, reddish gold between two banks
painted with wonderful spring
flowerings.
Out of that stream there issued living
sparks which settled on the flowers on
all sides. Like ruby set in gold and
then as intoxicated with the olders with
the odors they again plunged into the
amazing flood. As one spark sang another
spa spark emerged. The high desire that
now inflames incites you to grasp
mentally the things you see pleases me
more as it swells more. But first, that
you may satisfy your mighty thirst, you
must drink of these waters. So did she,
who is the son of my eyes, speak to me.
She added this. The river and the gems
of topaz entering and leaving, and the
grass is laughter. These are shadow
shadowy prefaces of their truth. Not
that these things are lacking in
themselves. The defect lies in you,
whose sight is not yet that sublime.
Okay. So he says this he's reached the
limit of his imagination. He can't
describe Petri's beauty anymore. And now
what uh Beatrice is saying to him is
that to truly experience God you need
your imagination to be limitless.
Right. And so drink from the light.
Do you have a question? Yeah, I have a
question like uh personally I find this
thematically a little bit weird. So
earlier on he was talking about circles
of angels and about light and about
Beatress being so great that he can't
describe her. And we have to notice that
these are all very abstract things like
he literally cannot conceptualize them
in physical manner anymore. However,
here he can suddenly conceptualize
things again. He's suddenly talking
about the river and about the flower
banks. So what prompted this shift and
what place does it have here?
Um, I I don't I don't agree with you. I
I think he's always been able to
visualize this. I think this is a very
visual poem, right? I mean, like, just
look at the artwork from here. I mean,
it's it's pretty visual.
So, at at no point did he actually lose
his imagination when when he's saying
I've reached a limit of my imagination,
it's just it's just telling u us and him
we need to work harder, guys. This is a
co this is a co-creation process. Not
only do I have to like work harder to
create the words to describe my
experience, but you have to devote
yourself further and invest your
imagination further to really truly
appreciate what I'm saying. Okay.
All right. So, the idea here is that
he's reached the limits of his
imagination. And so, what does Beatric
tell him to do?
uh not the water. What does what what
must he drink
the light? Okay. And it is but it is
metaphor described as water because why
would he do that? What is he what is he
really describing here?
>> Um I remember in the Bible in the New
Testament the Samaritan woman and Jesus
Jesus said if you follow me I will give
you the living water. So maybe it's a
metaphor for that.
>> Yeah. It's it's a baptism, right? It's
an initiation into faith. Okay. Right.
Does that make sense? Like when you when
you absorb this light, it is giving you
a new faith, a new light to truly
activate your imagination because that's
what you'll need if you're truly to meet
God. Does that make sense? Okay, let's
let's keep on going.
Verse 82.
>> Yep.
>> No infant who wakes long after his usual
hour would turn his face toward milk as
quickly as I hurried toward that stream
to make still finer mirrors of my eyes.
I bent out toward the waters which flow
there that we in them may find our
betterment. But as my eyelids eaves
drank of that wave, it seemed to me that
it had changed its shape, no longer
straight, that flow now formed around.
Then, just as maskers, when they set
aside the borrowed likeness in which
they hide, seemed to be other than they
were before, so were the flowers and the
sparks transformed, changing to such
festivity before me that I saw clearly
both of heaven's courts.
>> Okay? So, as he's drinking the light,
his very perception of the heavens are
changing. Okay? So, this is extending
his imagination. And this is
transcending his imagination. So now he
can he he can actually see heaven. Okay.
And when he sees heaven, he can now
describe heaven to us.
97.
Oh radiance of God through which I saw
the noble triumph of the true realm.
Give to me the power to speak of what I
saw. Above on high there's a light that
makes apparent the creator to the
creature whose only peace lies in his
seeing him. The shape which that light
takes as it expands is circular and its
circumference would be too great a
girdle for the sun. All that one sees of
it derives from one light ray reflected
from the summit of the primum mobile
which from it draws power and life and
as a hill is mirrored in waters at its
base as if to see itself when rich which
with grass and flowers grazed so in a
thousand tears that towered above the
light and circling it I saw mirrored all
of us who had one return above. And if
the lowest rank and gathers such vast
light, and what must be the measure of
this rose where it has reached its
highest leaves within that breath and
height I did not find my vision gone
astray, for it took in that joy in all
its quality and kind there, near and far
do not subtract or add. For where God
governs with no mediator, no thing
depends upon the laws of nature. into
the yellow of the eternal rose that
slopes and stretches and diffuses
fragrance of praise unto the son of
endless spring. Now Beatatric drew me as
one who though he would speak out it's
silent. And he and she said, "See how
great is this council of white robes.
See how much space our city's circuit
spans. See how our seated ranks are now
so full that little room is left for
anymore. And in that seat on which your
eyes have fixed, because a crown already
waits above it before you join this
wedding feast, shall sit the soul of
noble Henry. He who is on earth to be
imperial, he shall show Italy the
righteous way. But when she's unready,
the blind greediness bewitching you has
made you like the child who dies of
hunger and dries off his nurse. and in
the holy form such shall be the prefect
then that either openly or secretly he
will not walk with Henry but God will
not endure him long within the holy
ministry he shall be cast down there or
Simon may major pace he shall force the
the anac deeper into his hole
>> okay all right so again
um now Dante is able to see imp its
entirety and it's basically like two
roses and then the rows are seated um
those who are closest to God and we'll
we'll see their ranks uh later on and
this is this will be the last time that
Beatatric will speak and again they're
in the imperium
and what Beatric is talking about is a
prophecy okay so this is again the year
1300 uh Donnie Wolf finishes in 1321,
but he's right in the near 1300. A few
years from now, uh Henry VIII, the Holy
Roman Emperor will invade Italy and try
to unify uh Italy and then he will be
betrayed by the Pope Clement. Okay. So,
what what um uh Beatric is saying is
that Nova Henry has this divine mission.
Okay. He's almost like sent by God to
lead Italy in a righteous way. But
unfortunately Italy was not yet ready
for the grace of God. And so he was
betrayed and he failed in his mission.
And so uh the person who will who is
responsible for his failure is Clement
and and God will punish Clement as Simon
Maggus was um punished as well. If you
know Catholic theology, you know that
Simon Magnus is a heretic, right? The
first great heretic of the Catholic
faith. And so
it's it's troubling because we are now
in heaven, right? And heaven is supposed
to be the happiest memories, right? Just
pure uph.
And Beatrice is being angry. She she's
clearly angry about what's going to
transpire.
And
so what's going on here?
What? How? How can we explain or
reconcile this paradox where she's in
heaven
and this is the happiest memories of the
happiest people? There should be no
hatred. There should be no anger.
Yet, in her final words to Dante,
she tells him a prophecy of betrayal,
of
hatred.
What's going on here? Yes. Um, so like
like I said last time, I think maybe
it's because Dante isn't here to stay.
Like he isn't here to bathe in happiness
uh and to stay an angel or whatever he's
doing. He is here to carry a message
back to earth. And that's why she's
telling him all this. This this is like
the secrets. This is like the top the
pentagon secrets. And they're telling
them this in front of God like at at the
preus of God because that's the most
secret layer. And he's she's telling
them this so that he can carry the
message back to her.
>> And what is his message?
>> The message that uh all this is going to
go is going to go down and Henry is
actually a nice guy and all that.
>> Well, D knows that.
>> Well, he knows that. But the people,
>> right? In 1321. He's seen every
transpired. He was the one who wrote
letters to Henry praising him for his
efforts. But but again, it's like we're
we're in heaven and we're taught that in
heaven, you're able to let go of your
bad memories, right? You're able to
embrace your good memories. This is
clearly a bad memory.
What What's going on here? Uh yes,
>> I think maybe also Dante is trying to
weave his own political views into this
uh this story just because I'm not sure
since this is after all his imagination.
>> So So this is what most cars believe.
Okay, most scholars believe that Donnie
has this political vendetta
and he's trying to settle scores.
But for the past week, I've been telling
you guys that we let's work the
assumption. Let's work with the faith
that this poem is perfect and that
everything in it makes sense. And as
long as we're able to imagine hard
enough, have enough faith and hope and
love, we can make sense of what's really
going on. Okay? And to say, well, you
know, he was just angry and his
political band vendetta. Yeah, it does
make sense, but I want to try harder.
Okay? I want us to use our imagination
and figure out what's really going on
here. Why is Petra's last words to Dante
both anger and
hatred? I guess
>> so. This is probably a really far off
explanation, but uh I can remember like
both in my life and in the Bible some
cases when your anger is so righteous
like sometimes it's the anger of God and
it's so righteous that it feels like
joy. It feels like you're ex It feels
like you're reing in your anger and you
know that what you're angry towards is
right.
>> Um yeah. So you you're saying that
Beatric is um anger makes her happy.
Huh.
Um yeah, that's a possibility.
Uh but let's keep on using our
imagination, right? And Okay. All right.
So let's go to the year 13 1300. Okay.
and you are a Catholic believer.
What do the church fathers teach you
about evil in this world?
>> Uh yes, there are 1300 guys. Not not
today. Okay. Catholic church is very
different. Yes.
>> Evil comes from Satan,
>> right? But what do you do about evil in
this world?
>> The seven deadly sins. No, no, I'm
saying like if you see evil, if evil
happens to you in this world, what do
you do?
>> There there will be just retribution,
but you may not need to do it. There
would be a divine plan for it.
>> Um, okay. There's actually much simpler
explanation.
What What have people literally taught
at this time in history about evil and
injustice?
>> I think people just been taught do not
just against the god not against the
church but he just I think the dentist
is against church so maybe he's saying
this is quite evil
>> yes
>> maybe just accept it like
>> accept it why
>> because persecution is a way to make you
grow and like do not take things into
your own hands like it's God's job
>> yes it's all part of God's
Uh no, no, no, no. There's a really
simple logic at work here. Okay.
>> Yes.
>> Just like evil is within us, so it's
normal to occur.
>> But where does evil come from?
>> From the first uh sin, like Adam eating
the apple.
>> I understand. That was like 10,000 years
ago. So why is it still evil?
Okay. So this is hard. Okay. But at this
time in history, what the people were
taught is this. We are all born in sin
because of the original sin because and
that is transmitted to us through our
bodies. Right.
Right. What do our bodies want? Our
bodies want sex. They want money. Right.
Okay. But our bodies are just temporal
things. We'll have our bodies for 50
years, 100 years at most. basically 40
years. Okay, 40 years in the grand
scheme of things is nothing, right? So,
put up with this persecution, put up
with this evil, put up with this
injustice for 40 years, you die, you go
to heaven, and all you do is experience
pure bliss. Pretty simple deal. It's a
pretty good deal, right guys? You see
evil around you, you see injustice, you
see sin. Don't worry about it. It
doesn't matter.
What matters is your salvation. And your
salvation
demands that you keep yourself free of
sin. Okay. Uh yes.
>> So what you're saying is basically Dante
doesn't agree with that.
>> Exactly.
He completely disagrees with that.
What's he really saying?
when you see evil, you should do
something about it.
>> No, no, no. But, but I'm trying to
explain why Peaches is like in her title
words to Dante cursing
uh
like these people, right? Saying
Clement, he's going to burn in hell and
like uh the people in Italy are uh in
grateful.
Why is she doing that?
>> Yes.
>> So, um I'm confused about something you
just said. So you said that Dante is
against the uh keep yourself pure uh
doctrine of the church and he's against
pass pacitivity like not doing nothing.
Yeah. Yeah. That's what you said. But a
couple of classes ago you told us about
all that hope and light stuff. And when
I asked you why Dante wasn't proactively
trying to do some things and you said,
"Oh, he's acting in hope and light." And
when I asked you what that means, you
said that it means that he's acting
inwards and he's not acting outwards. So
I want to ask you how to reconcile this
like he's both doing something and he's
against doing nothing.
>> Okay. So first of all you need to
appreciate
um in our world the greatest action you
can take is to use your imagination.
Okay? That's what he's going to reveal
to us. The greatest act you can take
okay is to use your imagination. Which
means that being a poet is the greatest
thing you could possibly ever aspire to.
There is no greater people than poets in
this world. Okay? Not prophets, not
Jesus, not conquerors, not Napoleon, not
Charlemagne, not Julius Caesar, poets.
Okay? That's what living a life of
faith, hope, and love and love is really
about to write poetry that expands human
imagination. Okay. All right. So, let's
go back to the original question.
Why is Beatric bitching about the world
in heaven? Yes.
>> Maybe he's mad like this is saying that
some people are so heavenly bound that
they are not of no earthly good. So,
it's like people he's criticizing people
who are like thinking about heaven but
not doing anything about the earth.
>> Exactly. Yes. Exactly.
What what D is trying to say is that
guys, it's not that earth is a prison
and once we do our time, we can go to
heaven. That's not how it works. It's
all connected. Okay? What happens on
heaven happens on earth. What happens on
earth happens in heaven. As above, so
below. As above, so below. Does that
make sense? As below, so above. It's all
intertwined together.
just Beatus cannot be happy in heaven
because we're so screwed up on earth.
You understand?
And because we're so screwed up on
earth, we screw everything up. So don't
be like, you know what? Um, I see evil,
but I'll just go lie in my bed for the
next 40 years, and then when I die, I'll
experience bliss in heaven. That's not
how it works, man. That isn't If there's
evil on earth, there has to be evil on
in heaven. And that's why she's angry.
Does that make sense?
Okay. That's a message Dante has for us.
As above, so below.
As below, so above. It's all intertwined
together.
So Dante is trying to destroy the
escapist mentality, the defeetist,
escapist, pessimistic mentality of the
people at this time.
Right? You have to do something.
Yes.
>> Does that mean does does that mean the
earth, heaven, and hell is all
connected?
>> Yes. It's all intertwined together. Yes.
>> So So there must be um sins in hell
and evil in hell, right?
>> Yeah.
>> Therefore there there will be sin and
evil in earth and there will be sin and
evil in heaven.
>> I I I don't understand. So, so there
must be sin and uh evil in hell, right?
But they are all connected.
So, do do you get what what I'm saying?
>> But I think it's connected in emotional
way, not in like the sin in uh hell
transcends to heaven like you're saying,
but it's the sins in hell and on earth
that upsets heaven maybe, right? Like
emotionally, Beatress is mad, but mad is
not.
Okay. Yes.
>> Yeah. Like professor maybe I have a
question that I may need you help me to
clarify some concept about the
difference between like what we have
happens on earth and what has happened
on the heaven because if you're seeing
that like uh we no matter where we are
we can all feel or perceive uh there's
good in there's kind or there's evil on
both earth and heaven. How could the
heaven and uh we live in the real world
different?
Or in other words like um if we can feel
we can have the we can both feel the
same thing on earth and heaven then how
could those parts uh essentially
different from each other?
>> Okay. So the difference between earth
and heaven is that heaven is spiritual.
Okay. So we are souls right? Earth we
have bodies.
You understand? That's the difference.
Okay. So what we experience in on earth
is different from what we experience in
in heaven. Um and and what D is going to
discuss is okay why does there have to
be this distinction, right? Why is it
that we're given bodies?
And if you and again in the year 1300
the Catholic Church teaches you that
um
we have bodies because we are a failed
science experiment. Okay, do you
understand? All right. What Augustine
writes is that what are we made of?
>> What are we made of?
>> No, that's not what the Bible says. What
does the Bible say? We are made of what?
We're made of dirt.
>> Man, we are pieces of dirt. That's what
we are. So, how can we do anything
right? That's like literally what the
Bible says. We are made of dirt. Oxin
says that then if we are made of dirt,
that just means that we are a fail
science experiment. Okay? God didn't
mean to create us like this, but he did.
And now we're completely screwed up. He
has to put up with us. Okay? And so, we
just have to like endure. We just have
to like be patient. And then once our
bodies wither away, we our souls can now
escape to heaven. We'll have eternal
bliss. Yes.
>> Uh but that makes very little sense
given that first uh dirt was created by
God. So technically it's also a creation
of him. And second, God kind of molded
the first man himself. So if it's God
doing the creating even if it's from
dirt, then how could it be wrong, man?
>> Look look look look. Okay. I do not want
this to like be a theological class.
Okay? What I'm telling you is what
people in this time believed and what
I'm trying to tell you is how Dante
responds to this. You understand? I
don't want to have this argument. Okay?
You have this argument, go back in time
and go argue with Arinstein. Okay? All
right. Let's uh let's continue, please.
KTO 31.
So in the shape of that white rose, the
holy legion was shown to me. The host
that Christ with his own blood had taken
as his bride. The other host which
flying sees and sings the glory of the
woman who draws his draws its love and
that goodness which granted it such
glory. Just like a swarm of bees that at
one moment enters the flowers and at
another back to that labor which yields
such sweet savor descended into that
vast flower grazed with many petals then
again rose up to the eternal dwelling of
its love.
>> So there are two roses and these two
roses are like stadiums where all the
best people are placed and again this
creates a paradox because why do the
people of the Catholic church why are
they in one rose and then everyone else
is in another rose? Okay. Um, so there
are these paradoxes that make you
question the orthodoxy at this time.
Keep on going. Uh, Carol,
verse 13. Their faces were all living
flame. Their wings were gold, and for
the rest, their white was so intense, no
snow can match the white they showed.
When they climbed down into that
flowering rose, from rank to rank, they
shared that peace and aror which they
had gained. wings that fanned their
sides. Nor did so vast a throng in
flight, although it interposed between
the candid rose and light above,
obstruct the sight or splendor, because
the light of God so penetrates the
universe according to the worth of every
part that no thing can impede it. This
confident and joyous kingdom thronged
with people of both new and ancient
times turned all its sight and order to
one mark. Oh three-fold light that in a
single star sparkling into their eyes
contents them so look down and see our
tempest here below. At the barbarians
when when they came from a region that
is covered every day by Helis who wields
with her loved son were seeing Rome and
her vast works struck dumb when of all
mortal things the latter was the most
eminent. Then what amazement must be
filled me when I to the divine came from
the human to eternity from time and to a
people just insane from Florence came.
And certainly between the wonder and the
joy it must have been welcome to me to
hear him speak nothing. And as a pilgrim
in the temple he had vowed to reach
renews himself. He looked in hopes he
can describe what it was like. So did I
journey through the living light,
guiding my eyes from rank to rank, along
a path now up, now down, now circling
round. There I saw faces given up to
love, grazed with another's light and
their own smile, and movements grazed
with every dignity.
By now my gaze had taken in the whole of
paradise, its form in general, but
without looking hard at any part, and I,
my will, rekindled, turning toward my
lady, prepared to ask about those
matters that inclined my mind to doubt.
>> Okay. So,
Dante now has the vision to see the
entirety of the Imperium, the seat of
God. And he is the wilder. He's amazed.
He is stunned by what he has seen. And
he he's filled with tremendous joy and
happiness. And so, what he wants to do
is share with Beatatrice, right? He's
turning to Beatrice. He wants to lock
eyes with her and they want to smile
together in order to share this of
greatest of joys of being in the
imperium but she's now disappeared.
Okay, keep on going.
Verse 58.
Where I expected her, another answered,
I thought I should see Beatrice and saw
an elder dressed like those who were in
glory. His gracious gladness filled his
eyes, suffused his cheeks. His manner
had that kindliness which suits a tender
father. "Where is she?" I asked him
instantly. And Hube replied, "That all
your longings may be satisfied." Beatric
urged me from my place. If you look up
into the circle that is third from that
rank which is highest, you will see her
on the throne her merits have assigned
her. I without answering then looked on
high and saw that round her now a crown
took shape as she reflected the eternal
rays. No mortal eye, not even one that
plunged into deep seas would be so
distant from that region where the
highest thunder forms as there my sight
was far from beaches. But distance was
no hindrance for her semblance reached
me undimemed by anything between. Oh
Lady, you in whom my hope gains
strength. You who for my salvation have
allowed your footsteps to be left in
hell. In all the things that I have
seen, I recognize the grace and benefit
that I depending upon your power and
goodness have received. You drew me out
of out from slavery to freedom. By all
those paths, by all those means that
were within your power. do in me.
Preserve your generosity so that my soul
which you have healed when it is set
loose from my body be a soul that you
will welcome.
>> Okay. So what's happening is that
Dante has reached Imperium. He is about
to meet God which will be his happiest
moment and obviously he wants to share
it with Beatatrice. He's also grateful
for be for Beatatrice who has taken him
from hell all the way up to heaven.
Okay. Is Beatrice his love for Beatric
that has guided him throughout all this
um time. His journey for the cosmos, his
journey from hell to purgatory to
heaven. It's all because of Beatrice.
And at this moment when he is about to
meet God, something has happened. She's
been switched. Okay? She's returned to
her seat in the rose and she's been
replaced by another guide, Bernard.
Okay? And Bernard is the one who will
take Dante to meet
God.
This is like really really confusing.
Like who first of all, who the hell is
Bernard? Okay, we know who Virgil is. We
know who Beatric is. We don't even know
who Bernard is. And like why make this
switch at this crucial time when
when we are at the climax when we are at
journeys end right what would this
happen
any theories
before we
continue yes
>> so first I have a question so when we're
talking about Bernard I'm pretty sure
it's okay to assume that they're a saint
right
>> okay so some background Okay, Bernard
[clears throat] is a saint of the
Catholic Church and what makes him
important is he's almost like the first
love poet of the Catholic Church in the
Catholic tradition. Okay, does that make
sense? He is one of the co-founders of
the Knights Templar. Um so there's a lot
of romantic um stories behind him. He
what makes him interesting is that he
love he wrote love poetry to Mary not
Jesus not God but to Mary. Okay. And I
mean [clears throat]
the standard explanation for why Bernard
is a guide is because Mary is the queen
of heaven. There's God but the queen of
heaven is Mary. Okay. So basically um
[clears throat]
Bernard is Mary's servant and Bernard
will will use Mary's power in order to
help Dante see God completely. Did you
have a question where
>> my theory is like that Dante is very
modest so he he um wants you. No, no,
no. Dante is not modest.
>> Arrogant.
>> Dant is the opposite of modest. Okay.
You will not meet a less modest person
than Dante. But but keep on going.
>> So he wants he he's trying to show that
he's joining the ranks with the most
famous poets in the world.
>> But not well not one of the most famous
poets in the world.
>> The first love poet in like in the
church.
>> Okay. Right. So yeah. Right. So first of
all, he's paying homage to Bernard,
right? He's saying like you c I come
from this legacy which you started which
is love poetry. The difference is like
I'm not I I'm actually loving a real
person and you and you you you love you
know someone else. Yes.
>> Um so I think something that's important
to realize here is actually something I
learned in medievalism. So during the
middle ages even the late middle ages um
love when used in this context is not
always about sexual sexuality. It's not
always about husband and wife.
>> It's actually the opposite.
This is the courtly love tradition,
right?
>> And but like the courtly love tradition
is one part of the middle ages. It's not
all middle ages. The whole idea of a
feudal structure is founded upon the
fact that you love your feudal lege like
you love your wife and you love your
parents. It's like fidop uh feudal
version. Uh that's the first point and
the second point is that Wikipedia says
here that uh Bernard is also a reformer
of the Benedictings. Uh and I'm thinking
maybe Dante could be hinting at the fact
that uh he is that he is advocating for
a type of reform. These are two points
I'm just going to make.
>> No, but but but but I understand that
there's lots of reasons, but I'm saying
like the the main reason that most
people agree on is first of all, Donna
is paying homage to Bernard. Um the
other reason is that like the queen of
heaven is Mary and Bernard is considered
uh her greatest earthly servant. Okay.
Uh those are the most two accepted
reasons. But again, I'm having problems
understanding why is he making this
transition. You have Beatric. Yes.
Sorry, sorry, sorry. Um at the back and
then you
>> uh probably because uh his love for
Beatatric has reached his peak and so he
cannot use love as a force to ascend. So
they need to switch person for him to
love someone else and then ascend. Could
you explain to try try to explain this?
Okay, elaborate on on this idea.
>> Basically, we were in heaven and he was
saying all great things about Beatatrice
and idolizing her. And so, it seems like
it reached a peak and it cannot be
better. And so, as we said, love was the
force guiding him. And because it's a
peak to meet God, he would need like
another like more of this force. So
switching the person could be a way to
ascend.
>> Okay. So that's interesting. Okay. So
let me add to what what you're saying.
Okay. To make sure I'm following your
logic. So love is the force that got him
to this point. But love can take him
further. Is that is that right? Okay. So
he needs another force to take him to
God.
Okay. And what do you think this force
will be?
We just said not reason,
>> not desire. What? Huh?
>> What?
>> Imagination.
>> Yeah. Okay. So, he wasn't even here and
he he knows the answer. Okay. Love can
only take you so far, but if you really
want to transcend, it has to be the
imagination. Okay. So, that's a force
that's going to take him to the highest
heights. Okay. Love got him this far,
but to go even further, you need
imagination. Does that make sense? Okay.
Yes.
I was going to say exactly that because
also in the text uh he replied that all
your longings may be satisfied. So I
think that like Beatatric has sort of
like satisfied all his like you know
love towards her already. So that's why
she has to return. And also I have a
theory that like because he's going to
meet God and meet Mary, right? And he is
essentially a poet and he wants to share
this with the world. So he needs to
consult with like a poet like Bernard to
sort of like draw from him to expand his
imagination to be able to describe the
following process if that makes sense.
>> And has Bonnie does something like this
before he's considered a poet
>> in order to increase his imagination.
>> Yeah. So he kind of like So that's why
Bernard appears to him because he's like
this great uh love poet. So
>> yes,
he had Virgil before in hell.
Um well we we'll discuss this starting
tomorrow. Okay. But but he he actually
doesn't consult Virgil for his poetry.
Okay. Um anyone else? Okay. So So I I
want us to think about this. Okay. This
is like really hard, but I want us to
think about this. Okay.
Imagine
you have the world's greatest mother.
Okay, which is like Carol, right?
Obviously. Thank you.
>> But
She's been with you
all this time
and she's taking care of all your needs.
If you are truly to like like you know
like just she's fed you the best food,
she's taught you the best poetry, she's
loved you throughout. Okay.
If you are tr to truly grow as a person,
what must you do eventually?
You have excuse me,
>> you have to like leave, man. You have to
like tell her to go away. Leave me
alone, mom. Okay. That's
that's what Bonnie is doing right now,
right? He's saying, "But you've taken me
so far.
And I can't do this without you. I
couldn't have reached this point without
you, but now I must do this myself."
Okay.
So, this is a really hard But I'm saying
like, okay, so so let's try to connect
everything together. Um, you have to
leave your mother at some point. You
have to leave someone you love at some
point.
And we've reached a point where love can
only takes us so far. And now the
imagination must take over. Okay.
Why? What allows for the imagination
that
created conflict with love?
This is a hard question, okay? But think
about this, okay? When you love someone
and when you imagine, there has to be
it's it's there there's a contradiction,
okay? And how and so why how can this
contradiction be resolved by switching
Beatric with Bernard?
Love is focused on one person and
imagination's more diverse
>> and switching with Bernard because
Bernard is a poet. So
>> what is love? What is love?
>> It's an action
and it has to be directed towards a
person, a real thing, object. When you
love a child, what are you doing?
>> You hug him, kiss him, feed him good
food.
>> Yes. Okay. Okay. So, so, so, sorry, but
like when you wrote the poem, when you
wrote the poem. Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> How do you feel about yourself while you
you were writing the poem?
>> I wasn't thinking of myself. I was
>> Exactly. I was not thinking of myself.
You understand? That's the trick, guys.
I was not thinking of myself.
>> That's what love is.
>> I don't think myself. I give myself. I
think of the other person and I become
nothing. I lose my ego. Right. What's
the imagination?
Exactly. You're expressing yourself.
Okay. That is the contradiction.
Right.
So when D is with Beatatrice, he cannot
think of himself. Has to think of
Beatric. He's giving himself because
he's so much in love with Beatric. And
that's what allows him to climb
to heaven. He that's what allows him to
leave hell journey from purgatory and
climb heaven. But now that you must meet
God, now that you must fully exercise
your imagination, you must retain your
ego. You must express your ego. You must
manifest your ego,
right?
And and why would this be a problem if
you are a
priest or you know you're a Catholic
priest at this time in issue? Yes.
>> Because people were taught to um lose
your ego and be humble like Jesus was.
>> Yes. Yes.
>> Um because you're not allowed to marry
and you're definitely not allowed to
express your love towards a soulmate.
We don't know that. Okay. But but yes,
what the church tells us is that you
must be humble because your ego is a
source of all evil in this world. Does
it make sense? And what is like no guys?
That's not how it works. Your ego is a
source of your imagination. And you can
imagine good or you can imagine evil.
You imagine evil, there's going to be
evil. But if you imagine good, there's
mean good. Okay? You understand? But if
you want want to truly meet God, you
truly want to understand the world, you
must use your imagination.
All right, that's the logic here. Okay,
again,
he
now must switch to Bernard. So the the
so the pl I mean like it doesn't really
matter who Bernard is, but he must make
the switch if he is truly to meet God.
Yes.
>> So this is something I didn't get. So
earlier you said that Dante believes
that uh people can only love other
people. They can't love concepts like
God and when they love other people
their love excites their imagination and
their imagination brings him closer to
God. So why is Dante right now replacing
the person he loves with this crusty old
guy he has no feelings towards? Like how
is he trying to excite his imagination
to meet God here? There's no love here.
>> Okay. [clears throat]
So what love does is expand your
capacity to use your imagination. Right?
But now you must use your imagination.
Therefore you must focus on your ego.
You understand? The only way to obtain
love, okay, as a fuel for your
imagination is by being selfless, by
giving yourself, right? To not think of
yourself, to think of others. Now, now
you have all this fuel inside of you,
right? Now you're going to use this fuel
in order to project your imagination to
understand God. But to do that you have
to embrace your ego. Okay? You and what
D is going to do is in the final KTO
he's going to show that he's better than
God. He's superior to God because God
does not have imagination. He does.
Okay.
All right. Okay. So are we clear about
this? Okay. So again, there's a scholar
scholarly explanation, but then uh
there's my explanation. So do as you
will. Okay. All right. Let's let's keep
on going.
>> Verse 91.
So did I pray and she however far away
she seemed smiled and she looked at
looked at me. Then she turned back to
the eternal fountain.
>> Okay. So this is almost like a
graduation, right? where you know like
you're you're maybe the school
valadictorian
and you just have this entire speech
saying you like I love you mother and
everything I am I am because of you but
what what you're really saying is like
I've grown up now I'm going to leave you
mother okay that sorry
all right let's yeah let yeah okay
yeah let's keep on reading
>> um verse 94 Four. And he, the holy
elder, said, "That you may consummate
your journey perfectly. For this, both
prayer and holy love had sent me to help
you. Let your sight fly around this
garden by gazing." So your vision will
be made more ready to ascend through
God's own ray. The queen of heaven, for
whom I am all flame with love, will
grant us every grace. I am her faithful
Bernard.
>> The queen of heaven is Mary. Okay. Um
Why is this a paradox or a problem in
the Catholic church?
>> Yes.
>> Um Mary is the Virgin Mary and uh she is
kind of
she carried God's son. Okay. He carried
God's son and she's the Virgin Mary.
She's a virgin forever. And right here,
Bernard, you are here writing love
poetry about her.
>> Um yes. Because what we are supposed to
believe in is the Holy Trinity, not
Mary.
>> Yes. Exactly. Because the King of
heaven, it's Jesus, not Mary. Okay. But
Jesus Jesus isn't even here. It's Mary
that's here.
This is a paradox.
Why aren't why isn't Bernard invoking
Jesus, right? No, no, no. She He's
invoking Mary, the queen of heaven.
Right. Let's keep on going. Verse
102 to 103.
Just as one who from Croatia perhaps has
come to visit our Veronica, one whose
old hunger is not sad, who as long as it
is shown, repeats these words in
thought. Oh my Lord Jesus Christ, true
God, was then your image like the image
I see now. Such was I as I watched the
living love of him who in this world in
contemplation tasted that peace. And he
said, "Son of grace, you will not come
to know this joyous state if your eyes
only look down at the base. But look
upon the circles. Look at those that sit
in a position more remote until you see
upon her seat the queen to whom this
realm is subject and devoted." I lifted
up my eyes and as at morning the eastern
side of the horizon shows more splendor
than the side where the sun sets. So as
of climbing with my eyes from valley to
summit I saw one part of the farthest
rank of the rose more bright than all
the rest. And as on earth the point
where we await the shaft that had
misguided glows brightest while to each
side the light shades off. So did the
peaceful aura flame appear brightest at
its midpoint. So did its flame on each
side taper off at equal pace. I saw
around that midpoint festive angels more
than a thousand with their wings
outspread. Each was distinct in splendor
and in skill. And there I saw a
loveliness that when it smiled at the
angelic songs and games made glad the
eyes of all the the other saints. And If
my speech were rich as my imagination
is, I should not try to tell the very
least of her delights. Bernard, when he
had seen my eyes intent fixed on the
object of his burning fervor, burned his
own eyes to her with such affection that
he made mine gaze still more ardently.
>> Okay, let's keep on going. Okay. 32.
>> Kanto 32.
Though he had been absorbed in his
delight, that contemplator freely
undertook the task of teaching. And his
holy words began. The wound that Mary
closed and then anointed was the wound
that Eve, so lovely at Mary's feet, had
opened and had pierced.
Oh wow. Okay. Okay. [clears throat]
Let's these three lines are really
important. Okay. Let's try to figure
this out.
Where we we met Adam, right? We met Adam
in heaven. Where is Eve?
Where is Eve right now?
No, but I'm saying where is she right
now?
At Mary's feet. Do you understand?
Mary is a queen of heaven and Eve is
right beside her so lovely at Mary's
feet next to the queen of heaven. Okay.
Right.
The wound that Mary closed and then
anointed was the wound that Eve had
opened and had pierced.
What does this mean?
>> Yes. The wound at Mary's feet I think is
sin because e
>> is responsible for the original sin and
>> um
so basically Mary used to have sin but
since Mary's purified u Mary closed the
wound.
>> Yeah, this is really hard. Okay, this
but but like it's actually telling you
exactly what's going on. Okay, it's hard
because of cognitive dissonance. It goes
against everything you've been taught,
right? We know that Eve was responsible
for the original sin, which was
disobedience, which was pride, which is
eating the fruit. Okay?
What did Mary do
to me?
>> Mary gave birth to Jesus and Jesus died
for the original sin to be forgiven.
>> So, who's responsible for redeeming us?
Mary.
This is what she's saying here. No, I'm
sorry. This is what D is saying here.
Okay. This is Mary that redeemed us, not
Jesus.
Yes.
>> Why isn't it Jesus?
>> Well, that's what we have to figure out.
Okay.
Why is it Mary and not Jesus? Yes.
>> Um, I also wonder what Eve had open and
had pierced um is some veil and that is
a continuum between
um God and human that he pierced by
partaking that fruit.
>> Yeah. He she broke the love and the bond
between God and us. Right. And Mary
closed it. Mary Mary repaired the bond.
So she redeemed us.
But how does it make any sense? Because
it was Jesus that redeemed us, right? It
was Jesus that repaired the bond. That's
what we were taught. What what God is
saying is like, "Nope, it was Mary,
guys. It was Mary that did this."
So, I'm going to try a rudimentary
understanding here. So, uh, Mary gave
birth to Jesus. So, basically what Dante
is trying to say here is that Mary the
ultimate source of Jesus who saved us.
That's the first part. And the second
part is that uh Jesus is uh a man and he
cannot be a mother. And so his love his
love towards everyone. His love towards
his believers is abstract like is not
visceral. It's not visceral like a
mother's love towards her children. And
what Dante is trying to invoke here is
Mary's love, the motherly love, the
purest love that God has given us.
>> Okay.
What is the greatest miracle in human
history? What is the greatest miracle?
What defies our explanation?
>> Um, so much people believing in
Christianity.
>> Um,
well, I mean, if you're Christian, you
don't think that's a miracle. You can
just natural, right? Because we're the
true. And so, yeah, of course, everyone
should should believe us.
>> Could you repeat Yes.
>> Okay. The incarnation, the virgin birth.
>> Okay guys, there are two miracles,
right? First of all, Jesus sacrificed
himself for us. Okay, a god killed
himself for us. Then you had a woman
give birth to a god,
which is which is a good miracle.
I'm the second one, man. Right?
Like how is it possible for like a
mortal woman to give birth to a god,
right? How is it possible then?
What enabled Eve to give birth? Yes.
>> So for Mary's case, maybe it was her
faith, her willingness to be a vessel
for God that has shown her from the
initial sin.
>> Exactly. Do you understand? Eve
um was proud and she disobeyed. She
lacked faith in God. Mary had complete
faith in God
and that's what redeemed us. The
complete another faith in God is what
redeemed us. Not the sacrifice of Jesus,
but the complete another faith
of Mary.
That's what he's studying saying here.
Okay? Which means what? Which means that
we redeem ourselves.
We have the power to redeem ourselves.
We don't we never needed Jesus. We just
have to believe in Jesus and Jesus would
come to redeem us. But first you have to
believe we could redeem then we could be
redeemed.
Okay? So you see what's happening where
before you were taught to be passive, to
be humble, to accept the will of God.
And now you're being taught no you have
to be active. You have to use your
imagination. You have to use your faith
if you are to better the world. And the
example is Mary. That's why she's the
queen of heaven
because she was the most virtuous of all
of us. And if she were not that
virtuous, she she could have possibly
given birth to Jesus.
Okay,
this is pretty mind-blowing, right?
I mean, like what do you think as
Yeah, I think later the Catholic um
reforms and everything do bring um Mary
to a higher point like Dante has. That's
why we see a lot of paintings where Mary
is holding baby Jesus and Mary is more
exhaust exalted in a way than Jesus in a
lot of these uh religious paintings is
because of the fact that the Catholic
Church also sort of um agree well later
on with this idea that she's the new
Eve.
>> She's elevated. Exactly.
>> Jesus is the new Adam.
>> Exactly. So rather than just say this is
all heresy, this is let's just burn all
this. Right. It's like no, he's right.
Okay. That's a power of poetry,
right? That's the power of art because
it shocks you into a new truth that you
must accept. It might take time, but it
will work, right? So um this is why
starting tomorrow we will rec we will
learn like the real battle is actually
between the Catholic Church and Dante.
It's actually between Virgil and Dante.
Okay. But first we want to learn about
the cosmology of Dante. Okay. Starting
tomorrow we will go into the final war
between Virgil and Dante. And what we'll
show you is that this war continues even
to today. Okay. All right. Let's let's
keep on going.
Verse seven. Below her in the seats at
the third rank, Rachel and Beatus, as
you see, sit. Sarah, Rebecca, Judith,
and the one who was the great
grandmother of the singer who, as he
sorrowed for his sinfulness, cried Mer.
These you can see from rank to rank as I
in moving through the rose from petal
unto petal give to each her name.
>> Okay. All right. So again,
Mary is the queen. Eve is beside her.
And then as we move forward, as we move
outwards, obviously the people closest
to her, the people who are the most uh
virtuous, right?
Rachel, Beat Rachel and Beatric, Sarah,
Rebecca, Judith, if you were like a
practicing
Christian,
you're kind of shocked by this. Why are
you shocked by by this? Let's talk about
the year 1300. Okay. Would you be
shocked by by by this? Yes.
>> Because they're all women.
>> First of all, they're all women. And
also, they're they're mainly Jews, man.
Right. These aren't Jews. Uh Rachel,
Sarah, Rebecca. I actually don't know
who Jud is. And then you have Ruth, the
great-grandmother of King David, right?
Why do you have these people and not
like David, Moses,
Abraham, right? The patriarch is you
have the matriarchs.
Okay. So again, this reveals the
revolutionary nature of Dante. Okay,
let's keep on going.
Verse 13.
From rank to rank as I and moving
through the rose, from petal unto petal,
give to each her name. And from the
seventh rank, just as they did within
the rank above, the Hebrew women follow,
ranging downward, dividing all the
treses of the rose. There the wall by
which the sacred stairs divide,
depending on the view of Christ with
which their faith aligned. Upon one side
there, where the rose is ripe, with all
its petals are those whose faith was in
the Christ to come. And on the other
side, that semiircle whose space is
broken up by vacant places, sit those
whose sight was set upon the Christ who
had already come. And just as on the
side to serve as such a great partition,
there's a throne and glory of the Lady
of Heaven and the seats that range below
it. So opposite the seat of the great
John who always saintly suffered both
the desert and martyrdom and then two
years of hell serves to divide below him
sid assigned to this partition Francis
Benedict and Augustine and others rank
on rank down to the center of the rose.
Now see how deep is God's foresight.
Both aspects of the faith shall fill
this garden equally.
>> Okay. So this is really the first time
that we see Augustine reference. Okay.
and he's clearly in heaven.
And we talk about Augustine a lot in
this class because Augustine is really
is really the major theologian of the
Catholic Church at this time in history.
Um what is the paradox here?
There's a paradox in the line comedy.
How many times is a quoted in the divine
comedy
never right. This is a major theologian
of the Catholic Church. His book City of
God and Confessions are read by everyone
uh within the hierarchy of the Catholic
Church. You're you're forced to read
them actually if you are to join the
Catholic Church. And Don never actually
quotes him. Okay. And this is actually
the first time that we see Augustine
appear. So again, this is a very subtle
uh tongue and cheek um very paradoxical
um place to put August. Okay, let's
let's run away
verse 40.
And know that there below the traverse
transverse row that cuts across the two
divisions sit souls who are there for
merits not their own but certain
conditions, others merits. For all of
these are souls who left their bodies
before they had the power of true
choice. Indeed, you may perceive this by
yourself. Their faces childlike voices
are enough. If you look well at them and
hear them sing, but now you doubt and
doubting do not speak, yet I shall lose
that knot. I can release you from the
bonds of subtle reasoning. Within the
ample breadth of this domain, no point
can find its place by chance, just as
there is no sorrow, thirst, or hunger.
Whatever you may see has been ordained
by everlasting law, so that the fit of
ring and finger here must be exact. And
thus these souls who have precociously
reached the true life do not among
themselves find places high or low
without some cause, the king through
whom this kingdom finds content and so
much love and so much joyousness that no
desire would dare to ask for more.
Creating every mind in his glad sight
bestows his grace diversely at his
pleasure. And here the fact alone must
be enough. And this is clearly and
expressly noted for you in holy
scripture in those twins who in their
mother's womb were moved to anger. Thus
it is just for the celestial light to
grace their heads with a becoming crown
according to the color of their hair.
Without then any merit in their works.
These infants are assigned to different
ranks. Proclivity at birth the only
difference. In early centuries, their
parents' faith alone and their own
innocence sufficed for the salvation of
the children.
When those early times had reached
completion, then each male child had to
find through circumcision the power
needed by its innocent member. But then
the age of grace arrived and without
perfect baptism in Christ such innocence
was kept below in limbo. Look now upon
the face that is most like the face of
Christ. For only through its brightness
can you prepare your vision to see him.
>> Okay. So um
what Bernard is doing is listing the
ranks of the most beloved right starting
from Mary and keep on going. Okay. Um,
so at this time in history, there's a
major debate in the Catholic Church
about children, right? If you're an
infant and you die before you are
baptized, what happens to you?
Yes.
>> You ascend into heaven because you
didn't do anything wrong. So, you are
technically perfect. Um that that that
might be logical, but that's not what
what what they thought. Yes. Anyone
else?
>> Um because you weren't baptized yet and
you don't and you still have the
original sin on you, you kind of burn in
hell.
>> Yeah.
>> You go to purgatory.
>> Yeah. You're limbo. You don't understand
limbo because it's it's a more dilemma
for the church, right? because
um you didn't become a Christian so you
can't go to heaven but you did nothing
wrong you are free of sin so it's wrong
to put you in hell so they just put you
okay let's make up a new place called
limbo okay or purgatory and we'll put
you there okay because like we don't
know what else to do with you right and
what is and so in this heaven
uh what does Bernard say about this This
this actually a huge issue by non
Catholic church. Okay. Like like because
it creates such a paradox, right? So
what does Bernard say?
Yes.
>> Salvation decides where they go.
>> Well, that makes no sense at all. Right.
Right. who like why should it matter
what your parents do that's even more
than just
what does Bernard say
>> the age of grace has arrived so you guys
can now go to heaven now
or actually no
>> yeah so before you can go to heaven I
mean like
>> before you couldn't go to heaven now you
can
>> well the age of grace is the coming of
Christianity Jesus, right?
Anyone?
Hey, let's let's read it again, okay?
Because this is very perplexing.
starting from
>> 19.
>> Uh yeah.
>> Oh no, sorry. Um 40
>> 40. Okay.
>> Verse 40.
And know that there below dense first
row that cuts across the two divisions
sit souls who are there for merits not
their own but with certain conditions
others merits for all of these are souls
who left their bodies before they had
the power of true choice
>> okay so these are children okay and
these children these babies are actually
in the roles as well okay and this goes
against Catholic doctrine because you
have to first be baptized in order to
ascend and to heaven. Okay, so these are
babies. Um,
and so
they are in heaven.
Okay, come on. Going.
Verse 46.
Indeed, you may perceive this by
yourself. Their faces, childlike voices
are enough if you look well at them and
hear them sing. But now you doubt, and
doubting do not speak, yet I shall lose
that nod. I can release you from the
bonds of subtle reasoning. Within the
ample breadth of this domain, no point
can find its place by chance, just as
there's no place for sorrow, thirst, or
hunger. Whatever you may see has been
ordained by everlasting law, so that the
fit of ring and finger here must be
exact. And thus these souls who have
precociously reached the true life do
not amongst themselves find places high
or low without some cause.
>> Okay. All right. So, so what Bernard is
saying is that everything happens for a
reason. Okay. There is perfect justice
in the world especially up in heaven. So
these babies are here for a reason, for
a cause. Okay. Uh
>> verse 61.
The king through whom this kingdom finds
content in so much love and so much
joyousness that no desire would dare to
ask for more, creating every mind in his
glad sight, bestows his grace diversely
at his pleasure. And here the fact alone
must be enough. And this is clearly and
expressly noted for you in holy
scripture. And those twins who in their
mother's womb were moved to anger.
>> Uh who are those twins?
>> And
>> right.
>> Esau and Jacob.
>> Yeah. Can you explain?
>> Uh because their twins were conceived
and they were fighting inside the womb
and one is hairy and one is smooth.
Beautiful. They fought ever since they
were in the tomb till the very end their
lives.
>> Okay. So it's Jacob and Esau. Yes.
>> Okay. Let's keep on going.
>> Verse 70. Thus it is just for the
celestial light to graze their heads
with a becoming crown according to the
color of their hair. Without then any
merit in their works. These infants are
assigned to different ranks. proclivity
at birth. The only difference in early
centuries their parents' faith alone and
their own innocence sufficed for the
salvation of the children. When those
early times had reached completion, then
each male child had to find through
circumcision the power needed by his
innocent member. But then the age of
grace arrived, and without perfect
perfect baptism in Christ, such
innocence was kept below in limbo.
Look now the face that is most like the
face of Christ. For only through it its
brightness can you prepare your vision
to see him.
>> Right? So how does he resolve
this contradiction
paradox?
>> First I have a question. Why does Cain
get to be in heaven? I be because I
remember it's easy. Oh.
anyone?
>> Yes.
>> So I guess he's saying that even in your
womb, in the womb you have a soul and
your soul is different like this uh a
liberty [clears throat] at birth is the
only difference. So like if you're
inclined to be good or evil, it's
already decided when you are at point
zero.
>> Yeah. Okay.
Yeah.
So, what do you make of this
explanation? Right. This creates even
more problems,
right? What he's saying is that Jacob
and Esso, well, they were always going
to be enemies and that was that was
determined at the point of birth. Right?
So again, this is what makes divine
comedy so revelatory because paradox
leads to more paradoxes. Okay? We
resolve one paradox which creates even
more paradoxes which is like uh wait a
minute here.
What's going on?
The merit was always was determined at
before birth. Okay. So God can know
where you belong the moment you were
born.
Yes.
But I thought uh God gave us free will.
So God can't really predict any.
>> Exactly. Okay. So this is really
problematic. Okay. This is a paradox.
Now God give us free will. We can be
anything we want. We can do whatever we
want.
But at our birth,
we
have our own
inclinations.
What's going on here?
>> Yes.
>> I am doesn't really exist. So even
though as humans right we cannot really
predict the future but be go but because
like God is all knowing he kind of like
sees everything happening but it's like
different for him because there's no
concept of death
>> right but but but again this is a
problem because what you're saying is
that well god knows what would happen if
you didn't die for he would know what
kind of person you became but in that
case there's no free will then it's all
predetermined right there's a huge
problem
>> I don't think We should think of this as
being like predetermined.
I think we should just think of it as
like God can God can know what whatever
we're doing like throughout the expanse
of time.
So he doesn't like make he doesn't like
force you into a certain ending. It just
happens and he knows it from wherever he
>> he knows it then it's not free will.
Do you understand?
>> He knows but he doesn't intervene
though.
>> Yeah. So why does that like conflict
with free will? I'm I guess I'm
confused.
So why does he knowing everything that
has happened conflict with free will?
Like you can still accurately
>> Okay. Yeah. Okay. So I understand. But
like what we will
Okay, I Okay, that does make sense,
right? He knows everything that has that
will happen, right? Because he is God.
So yes.
>> Or is it also an inversion of
Christianity because Could it be that
the proclivity at birth we have is
actually positive, not negative. So we
all like all children who die at birth
would go to heaven.
>> Yeah. Okay, that makes a lot more sense,
right? That makes a lot more sense. I I
I don't see
how
we can be born evil, right? But if but
if that's a case, that creates even more
problems because then like every child
goes to heaven, right? And then like you
just run out of space eventually.
>> Yes.
>> How do you run out of space if heaven is
infinite?
>> Um well I mean
in order for free will to happen, okay,
you have to have heaven and hell, right?
Because I mean like just think about
this moral dilemma where now you're
incentivized to kill your kid, right?
>> Just kill them at birth. Then you be
ensure them they go to heaven.
>> Yeah. Right.
>> Um because they haven't because they
have free will. They haven't decided
that they believe in God yet. to the
children.
>> Um the children don't have faith yet
because when they are born they don't
believe in God yet.
>> Yeah. They have not made the choice.
That's correct. Yes.
>> So they go to um purgatory and they're
in limbo.
>> That's right. That is how what the
Catholic Church teaches you. Right. But
I'm just saying like but we have a
situation where there are children
babies who are among the blessed who are
among the elect. And is like wait a
minute here. How do they get there?
Right. And what Bernard's saying is like
God knows everything. God is perfect.
God knows exactly where you belong. He
also said that your merit is determined
at birth. Okay? So without knowing how
you live your life, God can determine
what your propensity is. This is all
very confusing, right? Yes. Um the
babies are in heaven because as you said
like if you're a parent the happiest
moment of your life is when your child
is born. So when that child was born
they gave joy and love to their parents
so they can go to heaven.
>> Okay. But like that creates even more
problems because first of all like which
parent is not happy to see their child?
Second of all, if that's the criteria,
then it's a parent who determine who
which child goes to heaven, right? It
could be like, you know, the mother's
having a bad day. He's really she's
really unhappy, right? Well, then now
your child's screwed for all of
eternity. That kind of sucks. Okay. So,
what I want to do is this, okay? Um,
it's amazing to think about. We're we're
like channel 32. We are in heaven and
all that's happened is we're even more
confused. Okay? So I I during lunch I
want you guys to talk talk some yourself
do research and figure out this problem
for me. Okay. When I come back give me
the answer.
All right. When we come back at 1:00
give me the answer as to how to resolve
this paradox. Okay. I'll see you guys
I'll see you guys after lunch. Okay.
Okay. Um so we have a lot to do today.
Okay. So let's start class. What is the
answer guys? Tell me what the solution
is.
Okay. So this is the hardest theological
problem in the the universe.
It is almost impossible
to solve. Okay. And um why this is put
why this paradox or conundrum is put
before we meet God is the only way to
solve this problem is through your
through love and imagination. Okay. So
it's almost like a warm up before our
meeting with God which is which is going
to really test our love and imagination.
So let's try to figure out what's going
on. Okay. So uh let's go back and figure
out first of all who is with Mary. Okay.
So there's a hierarchy, right? So Marius
is at the top. Eve is with her. Um and
then below her are Rachel and
Beatatrice. Okay. Then below them are
Sarah, Rebecca, and Judah. Who is
Rachel? Tell me the story of Rachel.
>> Yes.
>> One of the most beautiful wives of Isaac
or Jacob. Jacob.
>> Okay. All right. Okay.
>> No. No. No. That's Sarah. Okay. Okay.
So, we need to figure out first of all,
why are they where they are? They are
the closest to God. So, why are they
where they are? Yes.
>> Because they didn't have free will.
No,
>> they didn't have the option to choose.
So therefore, they did not have free
will.
>> Is it because they are ancestors
married?
>> No. Well, I mean, okay. All right. Okay.
So, let me tell you the story of Rachel.
Okay. So, Jacob is exiled from his
homeland and he goes and finds shelter
and refuge with his uncle uh Lhan. They
make a deal where Jacob works for Lhan
for seven years and then uh Lhan will
give him Rachel.
Seven years later um they get married
and on the wedding night they have sex.
When Jacob wakes up he finds the woman
he's had sex with is not Rachel but Leah
who is Rachel's older sister. Jacob says
to Lhan, "You've cheated me." And Lakhan
says, "It's not our custom to first
marry the the younger sister before the
elder sister. So we are forced to give
you Leah. But if you work for me for
seven more years, I will give you
Rachel.
At this point, if you're Rachel, what
are you going to do?
I'd be pissed, right? I'd be like, screw
you all. I'm going to go find someone
else. Okay. What does Rachel do instead?
She sticks around. Okay. And that
demonstrates her love and devotion to
Jacob. It is an example of the beauty
and power of love. That's why she where
she is, she is where she is. Okay?
Because of her her self-dedication
to love, because of her faith in God,
because of her love for Jacob. Because
everyone else will be like, "Screw this.
I'm going somewhere else." Okay? Because
I've been cheated. But because of her
love for Jacob, because her favor in
God, she stuck around and endured
uh uh being married to Jacob while also
Leah being married to Jacob. Okay, so
that's a example of selfless love. What
is Beatric doing in heaven?
What does she do to warrant her next to
God? We know Rachel. Yeah, good example.
Um and Sarah who is the wife of Abraham
she prayed and prayed for 80 years
before she was actually granted an only
son Isaac. Okay. So we so yeah these are
examples but but what's Beatric doing
here? What is Beatric's accomplishment?
>> Yes.
>> So um but Beatatrice kind of uh she was
dead already. So Beatric kind of gave up
temporarily her place in heaven to do
the great labor of guiding Dante from uh
hell to heaven.
>> Yeah. But I mean how did she get where
she is in the first place?
>> She died at child birth. She gave she
died giving birth.
>> But that's not an accomplishment, right?
That's because like think about the
millions of mothers who given child
birth. There's like literally billions
of them. Okay.
>> But she
>> uh Yes.
Um, she inspired Dante.
Uh, yeah. Or Yes.
>> She made a devotion or covenant with God
that she at least she had the will to be
devoted to God.
>> Okay. So, there's only one reason why
she's she she is where she is. Yes.
Could it be arrogance from Dante because
he puts Mary at the top of heaven and
that's because there would be no Jesus
without Mary and he thinks obviously
he's divinely inspired and but there
would be no Dante without Beatric.
>> Exactly. Yeah. Thank you very much. D
put her there. You understand?
So
So think about this. Okay. We have
Rachel who is the perfect example of
love and devotion. We have Beatric who
is there because she put because put her
there. Okay.
So now we have to use our love and
imagination to figure out how these
infant got to this rose so that they're
beside God. Yes. Dante
>> put them there.
>> Dante puts them there.
>> Not Dante. Dante doesn't even know them.
He doesn't even name them. Right.
Who put them there?
>> Maybe that that is Dante's own
interpretation like they deserve to be
there.
>> Okay. All right. So again, what's hard
about Dante is that you are forced to
use your love and imagination, but once
you do, the universe opens itself to you
and it reveals itself to you. Okay. Um
you're a parent. Okay. Let's all imagine
we are parents, right? and we have
our first child and for what the reason
at one or two years old the child dies
maybe at six months who knows okay now
at this point in our lives we can make a
choice right most of us will choose to
despair some of us may choose to have
another one but then there are certain
individuals who
because of their fa faith, hope, and
love. They say to themselves, I'm going
to dedicate the rest of my life to
celebrating the legacy of my child. I'm
going to put all the love that I have
for my child and devoted to others,
devote to the world, to celebrate my
child.
Obviously, this person would would
deserve to be next to God, right?
But what's the paradox? What's the
problem with that?
Huh?
Yes.
>> Why is the child there instead of the
mother who um
>> Well, yeah, that that's what I'm saying.
I'm saying the parent did all the work.
So why is the child there not and not
and not not the not not the parent who
did all the work? Because the kid
inspires their parent and so that so
it's it's so it's the death of the the
child enables them to share them love
with the world.
>> Sure. But but I mean like so right it's
apparently did all the work. It's
starting with all of the poetry. Yes.
>> Uh in the same way Beatatrice inspired
Dante death of a child can inspire his
parents. I I know but but it's a parent
who did all the work,
right?
So why is the child there, not the
parent,
right?
Why is Beatric in heaven and and not
Dante?
>> Because he decided that Beatrice would
be in heaven.
>> Right.
>> So the child is in heaven because their
mother decided that they would be in
heaven.
>> Exactly. You understand? Okay. Like if
you're God, right, and you and and like
you talk to someone says, "Wow, your the
life you led was so exemplary. I have to
put you beside me because I am so
bedazzled by your example because the
world is shine is shining so much
brighter because of your sacrifice."
Okay? But the mother's like, "Don't put
me next to you. Put my child next to
you." Right?
You understand?
So that's why the children are in
heaven.
Excuse me.
Yeah, the parents put them there, right?
And if you think about logically,
this resolves a lot of the paradoxes,
right?
Because again, if you are a if you are a
uh parent and your child dies, you have
a hard time explaining yourself why the
child died, okay? Or or like why is my
child not in heaven? Okay. So this is
the hardest problem
for uh theologians to solve. I I don't
think anyone has solved this satisfac
satisfactory. Okay. But Dante provides a
solution. Does it make sense to you
guys?
Do you do you understand how how this
logic works?
By the same token, we can also imagine
certain examples where
um
a child's death warrants him or her in
heaven immediately. Okay. So,
let's think think
like what 13 or 12. The guy fights
Goliath, right?
If he lost to Goliath,
where should he be?
He should be next to God, right? In
fact, if he were to die, he'd be more
worthy of God than if he defeated
Goliath.
Does that make sense?
>> Excuse me.
>> So, why would he be more worthy to God
than if he defeated Goliath?
>> Yeah.
>> He had complete faith in God even
without having the results he had
expected.
>> Exactly. Right. So, so why they're put
in heaven is not necessarily because of
their actions alone. It's because of
their of their the effect of their
actions on the people around them. Does
that make sense?
>> Oh, if so by that logic then he is no
more worthy if he died than he was if he
was if he actually defeated Goliath
because uh if he actually defeated
Goliath then the net effect upon the
people next to him is better.
Okay, again use your imagination. My son
David went to fight Goliath. Okay, and
before I was fighting, I was afraid of
these Philistines.
My son goes and fights Goliath and he
dies. What are the rest of the
Israelites going to do?
>> They will avenge David and fight back.
Yeah. If a child has the courage to
fight a giant,
then I would be ashamed
to not take up arms and avenge him. I
couldn't live myself,
right? So just use your imagination and
use your sense of love. If you were a
parent and you saw your son make this
ultimate sacrifice, you'll be compelled.
You could be the biggest coward in the
world, right? You could be afraid to
die. You could have absolutely no faith.
But to see your son die against a giant,
he had actually no chance anyway before
him take up arms
into fight into fight with faith that
compels you into action. You understand?
And therefore David even though he's a
Israelite and not a Christian, he would
have and even though he didn't really
accomplish that much, he just died in
battle like you know he would have been
he would have been right next to God.
Uh yes. Uh my imagination is telling me
that the death of a child will be
incredibly disheartening and if he
defeated Goliath then then a child
defeating a giant will be a sign of the
glory and the power of God and I think
that would be more inspirational.
>> Okay. Then your imagination doesn't come
from a place of love.
>> Okay.
>> All right. Okay. Does it make sense to
to to you guys? All right. We can also
imagine let's just say that Mary before
she gives birth to Jesus she has a child
and the child dies right where would the
child go?
Exactly right because if you the Mary
have all the virtue to give birth to
Jesus then your child must be virtuous
as well. Does that make sense? Okay.
So
um this is a way to resolve the paradox
and again um what Dante is doing is he's
he's presenting to you the most the most
the hardest theological problem in order
to excite your love and imagination and
and because only with that can you
actually meet God.
All right. So does that make sense guys?
Any questions? Yes. Um I'm a quite
confused about why uh if the mother is
virtuous then the son is also virtuous
automatic.
Why?
Like uh like born with
Okay. Yeah.
I'll I I'll try. Um he he did not say
that. What he said was um for the unborn
child the mother is the one whose belief
has put the baby into heaven. um
you know just just a personal sharing um
before having three beautiful children I
h in on earth I have two children in
heaven and it's because I believe that
they're in heaven I haven't had them
that they're in heaven
but it's not because I'm virtuous
[clears throat] it's because I believe
they're in heaven and that propelled
them to heaven
>> and and and I mean this is a beautiful
story so thanks thanks for sharing such
personal detail. Um, but if you're a
parent, you understand.
But if you're not a parent, then it's
hard to understand. You can't actually
reason this this out. Okay? That's why,
you know, Divine Comedy, it has to be
read over a lifetime. And it has to be
read from a place of love. And it's only
after you experience love for yourself
could you truly appreciate Divine
Comedy. Right? Um,
okay. So, this is not to criticize you.
This is to say that this is a life
lifelong journey. And again, this is the
hardest question in theology. What what
happens to infants who are not baptized?
Are they ultimately condemned to hell
and limbo? And what Donna says is that
you have to just trust in the infinite
justice and wisdom of God. Okay? There
are going to be these cases that are
impossible for us to reason out. But God
knows the answer. God knows that your
sacrifice is meant to put the infinite
in heaven and not yourself in heaven.
And so that God is going to honor your
request. You know it was you who did all
the virtue in the world. Okay.
So um in a case where the child is
relatively young but the parent and the
child dies and for whatever reason
someone else thinks that child should
not be in heaven and the parent thinks
the child should be in heaven. In that
case what happens?
>> Oh my god.
This is not um okay. All right. Can
someone answer this question? You just
have to believe that God is the ultimate
judge and God will, you know, consider
every cases, every possible scenario,
every hidden thoughts of that child's
heart. And then,
>> okay, look, [clears throat]
God is love. Okay? So, when you truly
love, God responds to you. When you
hate, God turns away from you. Does that
make sense? If you're like, you know, I
want the child to burn in hell, why
would God honor your request? That makes
no sense.
>> Not saying they should burn in hell. I
just say someone believes that they
shouldn't be in heaven.
>> Then then where should the child be?
>> Pugat,
>> right? That's well limbo is in hell.
Okay. All right. [clears throat]
Okay. And again, like it's not everyone
who gets to heaven. It's it's those
people those individuals whose stories
are so exemplary that they inspire the
world to greater love. Okay? Does that
make sense?
All right. So now we are moving towards
well this is the very last candle. Okay
33 and this is the greatest kanto of the
entire divine comedy. I don't know why
people just read inferno actually. Um if
you really want to understand Dante you
really need to read the last kanto. Okay
so let's read it.
Here we go.
Do we do we not finish?
Oh, I I apologize. Yeah, let's just
finish. Okay, let's let's make sure we
we we Okay, but but but we understand
the infinite problem, right? Okay.
>> Um verse 88.
I saw such joy rain down upon her. joy
carried by holy intellects created to
fly at such a height that all which I
had seen before did not transfix me with
amazement so intense nor show to me a
semblance that was so akin to God and
the angelic love who had descended
earlier now spread his wings before her
saying a Maria Guratia plenna on every
side the blessed court replied singing
responses to his godly song so that each
spirit there grew more serene oh holy
father who for me endure your being here
below, leaving the sweet place where
eternal lot assigns your seat. Who is
that angel who with such delight looks
into our queen's eyes? He who is so
enraptured that he seems to be a flame.
So once again I called upon the teaching
of him who drew from Mary beauty as the
morning star draws beauty from the sun
and he to me. All of the gallantry and
confidence that there can be an angel or
blessed soul are found in him and we
would have it so for it was he who
carried the pawn below to marry when
God's son wanted to bear our flesh as
his own burden. But follow with your
eyes even as I proceed to speak and note
the great patricians of this most just
and merciful empire.
Those two who there above seated most
happy to be so near the empress may be
likened to the two roots of this rose.
The one who on her left sits closest is
the father whose presumptuous tasting
caused humankind to taste such
bitterness. And on the right you see
that ancient father of holy church into
whose care the keys of this fair flower
were consigned by Christ. And he who saw
before he died all of the troubled era
of the lovely bride whom lands the nails
had won sits at his side. And at the
side of Adam sits that guide under whose
rule the people thankless fickle and
stubborn left on mana facing Peter Anna
is seated so content to see her daughter
that as Anna sings hosanas. She does not
move her eyes.
>> Okay. So we have Adam and Peter and
Anna. Okay. Anna is Mary's mother. Mary
is so virtuous that even her mother is
able to obtain a seat um next to God.
Line 135.
And opposite the greatest father of a
family, Lucia sits, she who urged on
your lady when you bent your brows
downward to your ruin.
>> Okay, we don't come to discuss this, but
Lucia would be the inverse of Ricardia.
Okay, whereas Picarda lacks will. Lucia
is the total representative of will.
Okay, St. Lucy of the Catholic Church.
um who basically
um
would rather die than to abandon her
faith. Okay. Um keep on going.
>> Verse 139. But time which brings you
sleep takes flight. And now we shall
stop stop here even as a good tailor who
cuts the garment as his cloth allows and
turn our vision to the primal love that
gazing at him you may penetrate as far
as that can be his radiance. But lest
you now fall back when even as you move
your wings you think that you advance
imploring grace through prayer you must
beseech grace from that one who has the
power to help you. And do you follow me
with your affection? So may my words and
your heart share one way and he began
this holy supplication.
>> Okay. So again Dante is using Bernard as
a model as a model. Right. So Bernard is
first going to worship Mary to u uh
humble himself before Mary and this will
give him the power to humble for don to
humble humb before God. Okay. This is
the very last kanto. Okay. We have come
to the end. Okay. We are we have come to
God himself.
All right, here we go.
KTO 33.
Virgin mother, daughter of your son,
more humble and sublime than any
creature, fixed goal decreed from all
eternity. You're the one who gave to
human nature so much nobility that its
creator did not disdain his being made
its creature. Okay. So again, it's
trying to emphasize that Mary
is uh more noble because she was able to
give birth to Jesus. She she was able to
be the portal for God to manifest
himself in this world, which has never
been done before. Okay, we're going
>> verse seven. That love whose warmth
allowed this flower to bloom within the
everlasting peace was love rekindled in
your womb for us above. You're the
noonday torch of charity. And there
below on earth among the mortals, you
are a living spring of hope. Lady,
you're so high you can so intercede that
he who would have grace but does not
seek your aid may long to fly but has no
wings. Your loving kindness does not
only answer the one who asks, but it is
often ready to answer freely long before
the asking. And your compa in you
compassion is in you is pity. And you is
generosity. In you is every goodness
found in any creature. This man who from
the deepest hollow in the universe up to
this height has seen the lives of
spirits one by one now pleads with you
through grace to grant him so much
virtue that he may lift his vision
higher still may lift it toward the
ultimate salvation.
And I who never burned for my own vision
more than I burned for his, do offer you
all of my prayers and pray that they may
not fall short. That with your prayers
you may disperse all of the clouds of
his mortality so that the highest joy be
his to see.
This too, O queen who can do what you
would. I ask of you that after such a
vision his sentiments preserve their
perseverance. May your protection curb
his mortal passion. see how many saints
with her they join my prayers they clasp
their hands to you.
>> Okay so again this is such a
revolutionary
um passage. Okay so Bernard is praying
to Mary and says Mary please lend Dante
some of your virtue so that he may see
um God.
And first of all, what does it mean to
say
he may lift his vision higher still? May
lift it toward the ultimate salvation.
How can Dante see God
>> by having faith?
>> Not faith.
>> Feel
it.
What what does higher vision mean?
The imagination. Okay. So, this is
really interesting that he's saying that
Dante when he stares at God, you can't
look at with your eyes. You have to look
at with your imagination.
Okay.
Question.
What What does Bernard mean by he says,
"I never burned for my own vision more
than I burned for his.
What does he mean by this?
I never burn for my own vision more than
I burned for his.
He hopes that go Dante sees God more
than he hopes he will see God.
>> Okay.
>> Basically, he loves Dante.
That's a good try, but that doesn't
really make any sense, right? Because
Bernard is with God every single day,
all the time for all eternity. So, how
can he So, how can Donnie know God more
more than Bernard?
I never burn for my own vision more than
I burn for for his. What does this mean?
Does he realize that Dante's going to go
back to Earth and be able to take the
word of God back with him?
>> Yeah, that's what Donnie is here for.
But it's not the word, right?
It's his vision.
Yeah. So uh earlier you told us that in
heaven it's just constant joy of all
kind on the whiteboard and I'm just
reminded of the old and tired argument
if everything is joy then how do you
tell joy from sadness? So maybe Dante is
able to perceive God's joy more because
he has experienced sorrow in the human
realm for so long while Bernard has been
here for a while I guess.
>> Yeah. But
I I understand that. But I'm like,
would Donnie know God better than
Bernard?
>> Yes.
>> Uh he's being able to imagine more.
>> Yeah. So what is going on here is that
what Bernard is saying is like the only
way to see God is through the
imagination. Guess what? We angels, we
souls, we don't have an imagination. Why
not?
Excuse me? No, no, no. There's actually
a very good reason why they lack an
imagination.
It's they don't have a body. Okay. Okay.
This is like Dante explained to us. You
need a body to have emotions. And
emotions is what gives you memory which
allows for the imagination. Okay.
Um, so that's what Bernard is saying.
He's saying like, "Yes, we've been with
God for all of eternity, but we don't
really know God. Only Dante with his
imagination can truly understand God."
Okay, that's literally what he's saying.
All right. Uh, let's keep on going.
Verse 40. The eyes that are revered and
loved by God now fixed upon the
supplicant showed us how welcome such
devotions are to her. Then her eyes
turned to the eternal light there. Do
not think that any creature's eye can
find its way as clearly as her sight.
And I, who now was nearing him who is
the end of all desires as I ought,
lifted my longing to its ardent limit.
Bernard was signaling. He smiled to me
to turn my eyes on high, but I already
was doing what he wanted me to do.
Because my sight, becoming pure, was
able to penetrate the ray of light more
deeply. That light sublime, which in
itself is true. From that point on, what
I could see was greater than speech can
show. At such a sight, it fails. And
memory fails when faced with such
excess.
>> Okay. So what Dian is doing is he's
staring at God and it really really
sucks. Okay? It's burning his eyes so
much that it's destroying it. That's
almost like causing his brain to be on
fire and he's losing control and it's so
powerful
the site that he's also losing his
memory. Okay? He's basically lost his
memory. It's so traumatic that he can't
process what he's seeing. Okay. Uh, keep
on going.
>> Verse 58.
As one who sees within a dream and later
the passion that had been imprinted
stays, but nothing of the rest returns
to mind. Such am I, for my vision almost
fades completely, yet it still distills
within my heart the sweetness that was
born of it.
>> Okay, so he can't see anything. He can't
remember anything.
What what is left?
The emotion of it, right? Okay. That's
the only thing that's left.
The sweetness of it, the emotion of it.
And from this he's he has to construct
before his imagination the divine
comedy. Okay, keep on going.
Line 64.
So as the snow beneath the sun unsealed
and so on the light leaves beneath the
wind the oracles of civil wrote were
lost. Oh highest light you raise so far
above the minds of mortals to my memory
give back something of your epiphany and
make my tongue so powerful that I may
leave to people of the future one gleam
of the glory that is yours. For by
returning somewhat to my memory and
echoing a while within these lines, your
victory will be more understood. Where
is Dante now? Where is he? What? Yeah,
he's home. Okay, this is like 20 years
afterwards. Okay, so he was he met God
in the year 1300 during the Easter
weekend. Now 20 years later,
uh
he is now trying to remember
what he saw through his imagination.
Okay, he's trying to reimagine what he
saw. Did you have a question? Okay. All
right. Keep on going.
>> Verse 76.
The living ray that I endured was so
acute that I believe I should have gone
astray had my eyes turned away from it.
I can recall that I because of this was
bolder and sustaining it until my vision
reached the infinite goodness. Oh grace
abounding through which I presumed to
set my eyes on the eternal light so long
that I spent all my sight on it. In its
prof profoundity I saw and gathered and
bound by love into one single volume
what in the universe seems separate
scattered substances accidents and
dispositions as if conjoined in such a
way that what I tell is only rudimentary
>> okay so what is able to reimagine is the
totality of the universe okay everything
is connected together all right keep on
going
>> verse 91
I think I saw the universal uh I think I
saw the universal shape which that not
takes for speaking this. I feel a joy
that is more ample at one moment brings
more forgetfulness to me than 25
centuries have brought to the endeavor
that startled Neptune with the Argo
shadow. So was my mind completely
wrapped in tent steadfast and motionless
gazing and it grew even more unckindled
as it watched. Whoever sees that light
is soon made such that it would be
impossible for him to set that light
aside for other sight. Because the good,
the object of the will is fully gathered
in that light. Outside that light, what
there is perfect is defective. What
little I recall is to be told from this
point on in words more weak than those
of one whose infant tongue still bathes
at the breast. And not because more than
one simple semblance was in the living
light at which I gaze. For it is always
what it was before, but through my sight
which as I gaze grew strong grew
stronger. That soul appearance even as I
altered seemed to be changing.
>> Okay. So what he's staring at, okay,
what he's recognizing he's staring at is
the big bang. Do you understand? The
universe in its totality before it
became the universe.
He's also staring at the universe after
the big bang. Okay? Okay. So this is
beyond time and space. This is both
nothing and everything. Okay. This is
both the beginning and the end. The
alpha and the omega. This is everything
and nothing. Okay. Keep on going.
>> Line 114.
>> Okay. And this is what God is. He's he's
try he's tried for 20 years to figure
out what he saw. And he's he's searched
through the universe. He's used his
imagination and now he comes to the
fundamental understanding of what God
really is. Okay.
>> Line 114.
In the deep and bright essence of that
exalted light, three circles appeared to
me. They had three different colors, but
all of them were of the same dimension.
One circle seemed reflected by the
second, as rainbow is by rainbow, and
the third seemed fire breathed equally
by those two circles.
>> Okay. So, what is God
exactly? There you go. Problem solved.
Holy Trinity. We can now go home. Okay.
What the church has taught us for the
past 2,000 years is true. It is in fact
the Holy Trinity. And that's what you're
taught usually. Okay.
But you keep on reading and it's a
problem. Okay, keep on going.
Verse one, two, one. How incomplete a
speech, how weak when set against my
thought. And this to what I saw as such
to call it little is too too much.
Eternal light. You only dwell within
yourself. And only you know you self-
knowing, self- known. You love and smile
upon yourself. That circle which
begotten so appeared in you was light
reflected when my eyes had watched it
with attention for some time within
itself and colored like itself to me
seemed painted with our effigy. so that
my sight was set on it completely.
>> Okay. What's the problem with with with
this?
There's a problem here. It's the Holy
Trinity, but it's not the Holy Trinity.
Why?
What's inside the circle?
What's effigy mean?
It's us.
Yeah.
Okay. There's three circles. That's a
holy trinity. And um we're inside each
circle.
Yeah. Huh. Oh. Well, huh. All right.
Let's keep on going.
Verse 133.
As the geometer intently seeks to square
the circle, but he cannot reach through
thought on thought the principle he
needs. So I searched that strange sight.
I wish to see the way in which our human
effigy suited the circle and found place
in it.
>> So he's trying to figure out why we're
in the circle. Why are we in God?
Okay, keep on going.
>> Verse 139.
And my own wings were far too weak for
that. But then my mind was struck by a
light that flashed and with this light
received what it had asked. Here force
failed my high fantasy, but my desire
and will were moved already like a wheel
revolving uniformly by the love that
moves the sun and the other stars.
>> And so he figures it out. And when he
point the moment he figures it out, he
is completely connected to the universe.
He becomes one with God. Okay. So, and
this is how divine comedy ends.
Okay.
Um,
and so the question for us is what did
he see?
Okay. And again,
to solve this mystery, to solve this
paradox, you have to use your love and
imagination.
Okay. So all right let's try to figure
it out. All right, first thing I want to
do is look at happiness.
We are in heaven. We are beside with God
which is the purest happiness is eternal
bliss, the greatest joy. Okay. And we
have examples
of
joy and happiness on this board. Okay.
So let's just see these things are in
heaven to make to to make sure we
understand what heaven is.
Selfless sacrifice.
Is that in heaven?
How how do you sacrifice yourself in
heaven?
Well, sure. But what about sacrifice?
Yeah. So sacrifice is not here. You
can't sacrifice yourself in heaven,
right? Because nothing sacrifice for.
It's already perfection.
Uh novelty, surprise, shock.
Yes or no? Definitely no. Because it's
perfection, right? It's eternal. You
already know what's there.
No.
Relieve and release.
No, because you need tension for that,
right? You need evil, you need hatred,
you need conflict, you need agony for
there to be reflect, relief, and
release. Nope. Wish fulfillment, is it
there?
Uh, no. Because
Yeah, exactly. Right. There's nothing to
fulfill. Returning home. Well, maybe. I
mean, you you can say it's home. Okay.
Um, flow. Yeah, probably. self-creation,
self-discovery, sharing knowledge is is
that there no Bernard doesn't even know
anything. Okay, it's not there.
Connection, community, probably. Uh
recognition, validation, probably
beauty. Okay. All right. So, half the
things on the list are there. The other
half are not.
All right. So, where can where's the
only thing where we can find the rest?
here, right? Okay. On earth.
So, some of the happiness is on heaven,
some is on
earth. Okay. But the problem is the
problem is you're in heaven and you're
experiencing the perfect joy, the
perfect happiness. We already said
there's lots of happiness that are not
in heaven. So, how does heaven
compensate?
How does he heaven
resolve this problem?
As some people just don't have such kind
of desire. So no need to talk.
>> No, no, no. We just said heaven is the
greatest bliss. It is perfection. Is the
greatest joy. Every single moment is
pure bliss. We already said a lot of the
bliss
can't be found in heaven. So how does
heaven resolve this paradox?
Anyone?
Exactly. Okay. Earth and heaven have to
be combined together. You understand?
God and men have to be have to be
combined together in order to create
perfect happiness. Otherwise, it can't
be done, right?
Okay. So, we have to be inside God.
Okay. And what allows us to be inside
God?
faith, hope, and love.
>> Okay. Well, let's just use imagination.
Okay. The imagination. Okay.
Okay. So, it's the imagination
that allows us
to be inside God. Do you understand?
Yes.
>> I just I have a question about the first
thing. So this idea that in order for
heaven to compensate for not having some
happiness, it needs to combine heaven
and earth. Um
>> well, you need to have earth.
>> Like what do you mean by compensate? Is
it do you mean like for like a person to
experience all the happiness, they have
to both experience earth and heaven?
>> Okay, you're beatric, you're Rachel,
right? You're experiencing all
happiness, right? Where's this happiness
coming from?
By you seeing what is happening on
earth.
>> Yeah. Because we generate this happiness
on earth. And then because earth and
heaven correspond they experience this
happiness. When we experience happiness
they do as well. But the happiness we
experience they can't possibly
experience up there. So we have to
create it for them here. That's why
people like Rachel and Beatatrice are
celebrated in heaven because they
created so much happiness that not only
do they shine on earth, they also shine
in heaven.
>> Okay. Does that make sense?
>> So the idea is if you create happiness
on earth, you're also helping create
happiness on heaven.
>> Exactly. Okay. Because it is not
possible for heaven to create certain
forms of happiness.
Okay. Yes. And I think that also related
to like previously in the morning we
discussed like why uh Beatress is angry
even in heaven. Right.
>> Exactly. Like like so uh as above so
below, right?
>> Exactly.
>> Yes.
>> Where there's injustice in on earth
there must be heaven can feel it as
well. Okay. It's it's calling for us to
create happiness and justice.
Okay. Do you understand? And this again
is shocking for people at this time
because before they thought that her
earth and heaven were separated, right?
Earth is imperfect, heaven is perfect.
Earth is flat, heaven is spiral. Okay.
So this is a revolution in mentality.
All right. Okay. Does it make sense,
guys? All right. So we are in
God. Okay.
But at the same time, God is in us. How
why
how is God able to manifest himself in
us? So instead of in some of my research
about this um then like a scholar had
said that objective and subjective start
to converge and they were dealing with
this with sight. So like the seer, what
is seen and the act of seeing all
converge into one. So I wonder if maybe
if God is love, maybe this is the moment
where
my love, love itself and the person or
the God being loved all converge into
one because there's no time and space,
>> right? Okay. So exactly. So
God manifests itself in us through love.
Do you understand? So God is in us
through love. We are in God for our
imagination and this is inseparable.
This is what is the trinity. Okay? Does
it make sense?
Right? And there are two instances when
Dante
lets us know that God is love. Right?
The first is when he reconciles the Holy
Trinity. Remember when Peter
is testing Dante
and Peter asks Dante, "What is God?" And
God says, "What?" Do you remember?
Yeah. What does Dante say about what God
is?
>> God is love.
>> Yeah. For first of all, God is the Holy
Trinity, right? Jesus, the Holy Spirit,
and God the Father.
These are separate but equal. And so how
how do you reconcile this this this
paradox
because all three represent love. You
understand? So God is love. Okay. So
that's the first instance, right? The
second instance is the idea of the
mirrored flame.
So we are just a mirror that reflects
God and God is love. Okay? As
represented by a flame. Does that make
sense?
Okay.
So we are just a reflection of God in
the universe. So the way to appreciate
God is that God is in us with a force of
love and we are inside God through our
imagination. Another way of of
understanding this is that God is
perfection. So therefore God cannot
extend the parameters of perfection.
Right? To extend perfection is to say
it's imperfect. So the only way to
resolve this paradox is for us because
we are imperfect and through our
imagination we extend the boundaries of
the universe. Therefore we let God know
itself more.
Right? So it was it's only Dante in his
with his body with his imperfect body
that's able to imagine what God is
not Bernard not any angels not even Mary
okay and certainly God not God itself
God doesn't even know what it is it's
Dante that's able to explain to us what
God is
okay
>> but you're not saying that God only
exists because of man
>> uh no I didn't say that.
>> Okay. Yeah. I just wanted to make sure.
>> Okay. Yeah. Yes.
>> It reminds me of languages like uh
yesterday we heard Italian and I'm
pretty sure none of us here speak
Italian fluently. So if you speak a
language fluently then all it sounds to
you all it sounds to you is like
information. It's a information and
that's the state that Bernard and Mary
and every every angel is in. But if you
don't understand a language and you
listen to it and you can hear the
cadence and you can hear the rhythm and
that's where Dante is at.
>> Okay. I didn't really understand the the
point. Can you rephrase?
>> So if you understand the language then
people are speaking information to you.
If you don't if you do not understand
the language then people are speaking a
song to you.
>> I I I don't really understand that.
Okay. All right. Um sorry. Okay. Um
Okay. So what Dante is saying ultimately
is that the imagination
is the animating force of the universe.
Okay. So rather than see heaven as
separate rather than seeing God separate
see us as humans as part of the divine
creation process. And so you have a
responsibility to imagine.
Okay? Does that make sense? All right.
So,
um, you're like, "Okay, well, I
understand because that's what Disney
movies teach me or whatever." You know,
it's what's a big deal here? It's a big
deal because what the context is the
year 1300. All right. So, what I want to
do now is I want to com contrast this
with another
um passage from the Bible. Okay. So this
is what what's what's called part of the
apocalyptic tradition. Okay. Apocalypse.
Apocalypse is Greek for revelation.
All right. What is revealed to you? And
of course there are
in the Bible three
really famous apocalyptic um books.
There is the book of revelation, the the
book of revelation of John. There is the
book of Daniel and there's the book of
Ezekiel. Ezekiel. Okay. And in actually
in Ezekiel, we have a situation where um
also Ezekiel visits God. Okay. And we're
going to contrast what that experience
is like. So, so, so, so can we read
Ezekiel 1-3? 1-3. So,
just just say one and and and then you
know. Okay. So, so, so we're going to
compare contrast what Dante experienced
and what Ezekiel experienced.
>> Ezekiel Ezekiel 1.
In my 30th year, in the fourth month of
the fifth day, while I was among the
exiles of the Cabar River, the heavens
were opened and I saw visions of God. On
the fifth of the month, it was the fifth
year of the exile of King Jehoakin. The
word of the Lord came to Ezekiel the
priest, the son of Boozie by the Kabar
River in the land of the Babylonians. He
there the hand of the Lord was on him. I
looked and I saw a windstorm coming out
of the north, an immense cloud with
flashing lightning and surrounded by
brilliant light. The center of the fire
looked like glowing metal. And in the
fire was what looked like four living
creatures. In appearance, their form was
human, but each of them had four faces
and four wings. Their legs were
straight. Their feet were like those of
a calf and gleamed like burnished
bronze. Under their wings, on their four
sides, they had human hands. All four of
them had faces and wings, and the wings
of one touched the wings of another.
Each one went straight ahead. They did
not turn as they moved. Their faces look
like this. Each of the four had the face
of a human being. And on the right side,
each had the face of a lion. On the
left, the face of an ox. Each also had
the face of an eagle. Such were their
faces. They each had two wings spreading
out upward. Each wing touching that of
the creature on Whoops.
>> What?
>> Um, it was just on either side. And each
had two other wings covering its body.
Each one went straight ahead. Wherever
the spirit would go, they would go
without turning as they went. The the
appearance of the living creatures was
like burning coals of fire and like
torches. Fire moved back and forth among
the creatures. It was bright and
lightning flashed out of it. The
creatures sped back and forth like
flashes of lightning. As I looked at the
living creatures, I saw a wheel on the
ground beside each creature with its
four faces. This was the appearance and
structure of the wheels. They sparkled
like topaz, and all four looked alike.
Each appeared to be made like a wheel
intersecting a wheel. As they moved,
they would go in any one of the four
directions the creatures faced. The
wheels did not change direction as the
creatures went. Their rims were high and
awesome, and all four rims were full of
eyes all around. When the living
creatures moved, the wheels beside them
moved. And when the living creatures
rose from the ground, the wheels also
rose. Wherever the spirit would go, they
would go, and the wheels would rise
along with them, because the spirit of
the living creatures was in the wheels.
When the creatures moved, they also
moved. When the creatures stood still,
they also stood still. And when the
creatures rose from the ground, the
wheels rose along with them, because the
spirit of the living creatures was in
the wheels. Spread out above the heads
of the living creatures was what looked
something like a vault, sparkling like
crystal and awesome. Under the vault,
their wings were stretched out one
toward the other, and each had two wings
covering its body. When the creatures
moved, I heard the sound of their wings,
like the roar of rushing water, like the
voice of the Almighty, like the tumult
of an army. When they stood still, they
lowered their wings. Then there came a
voice from above, the vault over their
heads that they stood with their lowered
wings. Above the vault over their heads
was what looked like a throne of lapis
lazily. And high above on the throne was
a figure like that of a man. I saw that
from what appeared to be his waist up he
looked like glowing metal as if full of
life and that from there down he looked
like fire and brilliant light surrounded
him. Like the appearance of a rainbow in
the clouds on a rainy day, so was the
radiance around him. This was the
appearance of the likeness of the glory
of the Lord. When I saw it, I fell face
down and I heard the voice of one
speaking.
>> Okay, let let's go on to number two.
Okay, so you guys understand what's
going on, right? I want you to compare
contrast this with Dante's
meeting with God because this is another
meeting of God, right?
>> Ezekiel 2, he said to me, "Son of man,
stand up on your feet and I will speak
to you." As he spoke, the spirit came
into me and raised me to my feet, and I
heard him speaking to me. He said, "Son
of man, I'm sending you to the
Israelites, to a rebellious nation that
has rebelled against me. They and their
ancestors have been involved against me
to this very day. The people to whom I'm
sending you are obstinate and stubborn.
Say to them, "This is what the sovereign
Lord says." And whether they listen or
fail to listen, for they're a rebellious
people, they will know that a prophet
has been among them. And you, son of
man, do not be afraid of them or their
words. Do not be afraid through briars
and thorns are all around you and live
among scorpions. Do not be afraid of
what they say, or be terrified by them,
though they are a rebellious people. You
must speak my words to them, whether
they listen or fail to listen, for they
are rebellious. But you, son of man,
listen to what I say to you. Do not
rebel like that rebellious people. Open
your mouth and eat what I give you."
Then I looked, and I saw a hand
stretched out to me, and it was a
scroll, which he unrolled before me. On
both sides of it were written words of
lament, and mourning, and woe. Okay. And
we'll we'll do Ezekiel 3. Okay.
>> And then we'll we'll stop.
>> Ezekiel 3. And he said to me, "Son of
man, eat what is before you. Eat this
scroll. Then go and speak to the people
of Israel." So I opened my mouth and he
gave me the scroll to eat. Then he said
to me, "Son of man, eat this scroll I'm
giving you and fill your stomach with
it." So I ate it and it tasted as sweet
as honey in my mouth. He then said to
me, "Son of man, go now to the people of
Israel and speak my words to them.
You're not being sent to a people of
obscure speech and strange language, but
to the people of Israel, not to many
peoples of obscure speech and strange
language whose words you cannot
understand. Surely, if I had sent you to
them, they would have listened to you."
But the people of Israel are not willing
to listen to you because they're not
willing to listen to me. For all the
Israelites are hardened and obstinate.
But I will make you as unyielding and
hardened as they are. I will make your
forehead like the hardest stone, harder
than flint. Do not be afraid of them or
terrified by them, though they are a
rebellious people. And he said to me,
"Son of man, listen carefully and take
to heart all the words I speak to you.
Go now to your people in exile and speak
to them. Say to them, "This is what the
sovereign Lord says, whether they listen
or fail to listen." Then the spirit
lifted me up and I heard behind me a
loud rumbling sound as the glory of the
Lord rose from the place where it was
standing. It was the sound of the wings
of the living creatures rushing against
each other and the sound of the wheels
beside them. A loud rumbling sound. The
spirit then lifted me up and took me
away and I went in bitterness and the
anger of my spirit with the strong hand
of the Lord on me.
>> Stop. Okay. All right. Okay. So, do you
guys There's a major difference between
Dante and Ezekiel. Okay. Ezekiel is very
much part of the biblical apocalyptic
the apocalyptic tradition. Okay. So we
have Ezekiel and we have Dante. I want
to compare and contrast
these two. All right. What what are the
differences you see?
Let's let's just name them. Anyone? Yes.
Ezekiel thinks h uh humans and people
are bad and
you don't it doesn't matter what they do
just be good yourself.
>> Okay. So Ezekiel says that the
Israelites are bad. Okay. Yes. Yes.
So God is judgmental.
Is God judgmental in Dante? Okay. So God
is love. That's a major difference.
First, God is judgmental
in Ezekiel, but in Dante, God is love.
Okay. He's not doesn't judge you. Yes.
>> And Dante feels like he's is more
general and Ezekiel
um describes a lots of details.
>> Okay. All right. So, another big
difference is that Ezekiel is explicit.
Okay. You cannot possibly misinterpret
his message. He tells you the Israelites
suck. Go tell me they suck. Okay.
Whereas Dante, he is much more
ambiguous. Okay.
Why would Dante be much more ambiguous?
Why is he not explicit? Yes. because he
wants um the readers to um there's just
multiple ways to imp inter interpreted
his words.
>> Yeah. Free will, right? He wants you to
make a decision as to how to interpret
his poetry, right? God has given him
free will to to interpret what he wants
to interpret. Right? Donnie was invited
to meet God. But God didn't actually
say, "Donnie, go do this." Right?
Donnie can interpret the meaning any way
he wanted. Right. So yeah. What else?
What are some other differences?
Okay. Um
so
In Ezek in Ezekiel, there's a
commandment. Okay? There's an order from
God, right? Whereas in Donnie, it's more
about vision and imagination.
Okay.
>> Vision is up to your interpretation, but
with a commandment or squirrel, it's
very written.
>> Exactly. Yes. Okay. What are some other
differences?
>> Just to add on that, I mean, just going
back to uh
the show 33 Dante mentioned that the
reason for the ambiguity and the vision
is because God to him keeps changing and
it's all it's it's amorphic what's the
what's the right word for it shapeshifts
>> right
>> versus Ezekiel who is I know God is like
a general like tells you
>> ABC if you if you don't do ABC that's it
>> yeah look if you read Ezekiel closely
there's almost like a mechanical
language to it okay it's mechanical
uh whereas with Don Dante, it's more
spiritual, organic. Okay.
Right.
What are some other differences?
>> Dante had to go through hell and
purgatory to see God.
>> Exactly. Okay. So, for Dante, it was a
journey, right? It was a journey, a
process.
And Ezekiel, it's a destination. He was
just he was just shown these visions. He
didn't have a choice in the matter.
There was no journey. Good. What else?
Okay, we can go on and on. Okay, but the
major difference of course is that
whereas Ezekiel it is a revelation. It
is something that is shown to you,
Dante is an act of imagination. Okay, it
is something that you must imagine
yourself. Okay. It is something that you
must actively create yourself. So it's a
creative process. Okay. Does that make
sense?
All right. So again, the purpose of
divine comedy is to change the world.
And so if you are
um in your 13 1300
and you grow up in Ezekiel tradition
where God is angry, God is scary, God
wants you to be afraid of him. Donnie is
trying to change that and make you
um less afraid so you can be much more
imaginative. Right?
So how does Donnie accomplish this?
Yes. But but what is about divine comedy
that allows people to lose their fear in
God and allows me much more imaginative.
Yes.
>> By saying that God is love. So and God
will grant those who turn towards him.
So in in perfect love there's no fear.
Oh in in the scriptures is perfect love
drives out fear. So
>> right but is singing saying it enough?
Yes.
>> I think it's because he's making the
unknown unknown. So like uh people are
scared burning hell. People scared of
what's waiting for them after they die
and
>> exactly that's it. Do you understand?
Every all fear is just based on mystery
on what you don't know. What Donnie has
done is show you the completeness of the
universe from hell all the way up to
heaven. Every aspect of the cosmos he's
revealed to you. Right? Okay. So um
let's do Shakespeare Hamlet the famous
Hamlet.
Okay. To be or not to be.
All right. So where's we we'll read this
together.
>> Okay.
To be or not to be, that is the
question. Whether it is nobler in the
mind to suffer the slings and arrows of
outrageous fortune, or to take arms
against the sea of troubles, and by
opposing end them, to die, to sleep no
more, and by asleep to say we end the
heartache and the thousand natural
shocks that flesh is heir to, to a
consummation devoutly to be wished, to
die, to sleep, to sleep per chance to
dream. I there's the rub for in that
sleep of death what dreams may come.
What we have shuffled off this mortal
coil must give us pause. There's the
respect that makes calamity of so long
life. For who would bear the whips and
scorns of time, the oppressor's wrong,
the proud man's contumly, the pangs of
despised love, the laws delay, the
insolence of office, and the spurns that
patient merit of the unworthy takes.
when he himself might this quietest make
with a bare bodkin who would fartle
spare to grunt and sweat under a weary
life. But that the dread of something
after death, the undiscovered country
from whose bore no traveler returns
puzzles the will, and makes us rather
bear those wills we have than fly to
others that we know not of. Thus
conscious death does make cowards of us
all and thus the native hue of
resolution is sickly over with the pale
cast of thought and enterprises of great
pith and moment with this regard their
currents turn arry and lose the name of
action.
>> So there is at Yale or he was at Yale
but Harold Bloom was the greatest
American literary critic. He's a huge
fan of William Shakespeare. Uh in fact
he argued that it was Shakespeare that
created more journey created was human.
Um but you know I I mean it's been a
while since I read Shakespeare but just
putting Dante side by said with
Shakespeare I am not that impressed with
Shakespeare anymore. Okay. I mean like
it took a long time for him to say what
Dante would have said in one or two
lines. Seriously. What what what is
Shakespeare's point here?
Why? What? Yes.
>> People don't die because they're afraid
of
>> Exactly. It's that simple. Okay. There's
really no
like great truth to what to what
Shakespeare is saying here. All
Shakespeare is saying is that people
don't act because they're afraid of
death. Why are they afraid of death?
Because they don't know what death is.
It's that simple. Okay. So, um maybe
someone can convince me that this is
great literature. But having read Dante,
I am not as impressed. But yeah. So, so,
so this is the basic premise here. Okay.
It is because of the unknown that
uh people are afraid and what Donn has
done with the divine comedy is revealed
the entire cosmos to the world. And but
then you're like wait a minute here he
just made all this up. Right.
Right. He's like why why would people
believe this?
And the answer is, let's look at some
pictures. Okay, let's look at some
pictures. Do you guys what know what
near-death experiences are? Near-deaf
experiences. Okay, so there's this guy
uh the the the the pictures that that we
Right. Okay. So,
uh the first picture. Okay. Yeah. Here.
Exactly. Okay. Okay, guys. Look look
look at the picture picture on the
screen. Okay. So there are people who
have these near-death experiences and
first of all what they describe is
remarkably consistent.
Okay, they talk about how when they die
they enter this realm which is beyond
time and space which is complete unity
and they meet God and God is pure love,
pure forgiveness, non-judgmental
all generosity. Okay, it is remarkably
consistent
and one of these people actually
remembered
um the visions from his or her
near-death experiences. And look at the
picture. It's pretty similar to how
Donnie described
heaven, right? where God and the angels
are this huge sphere of luminous light
and everyone is surrounding them. It's
pretty similar to what Donnie is
describing. Okay. Uh let's go on to
image two. This is a uh AI rendering.
Okay. This is like again just exactly
how Donnie described paradise.
You you see at the top all these angels
flying around, right? And you see at the
core is God itself.
It's pretty similar. And there's a
hierarchy as well.
Okay, let's um this is an artist
rendition of Dante and Beatrice staring
at the imperium, the angels surrounding
it and God. It's similar.
All right, let's go to the last picture.
And this is Dante
constructing the hierarchy of paradise.
So, not only did Dante
um
give people a glimpse of heaven, but it
attunes to what people instinctively
believe about heaven. Okay. Does anyone
know about near-death experiences? What
happens to people with near-death
experiences? Do you guys know?
>> Their life flashes before their eyes.
>> But what what happens afterwards?
they live.
>> Yeah. Okay. Okay. No, no. I mean, yeah,
I understand. Okay. Yes. That's why
they're called near-death experiences.
Okay. Rather than death experiences.
Yeah. But, but it's interesting because
like um they might be in a car crash or
they might have had a heart attack.
Okay. And they meet God and God always
asks them, "Do you want to stay here,
which is pure happiness, pure bliss, or
do you want to go back home?" And they
always choose to go back home. Okay?
Okay. And I'm saying saying like why do
they go back home and what happens to
them after they go back home? Uh yes.
>> Um it sounds really weird like how how
does God even determine this? Like uh at
which point do God stop asking if you
want to go home? Because I feel like if
he asked every time then there will be a
lot more people going home.
>> But why does God ask? Come on guys.
>> Do you want to go home? Like
>> why does God My bad.
>> Free will. Come on. We've been saying
this for the past five classes. Okay.
Free will is the fundamental law of the
universe. God can never force you to do
anything. God must always ask you. So
everyone chooses to go back home and
what happens to this person
to me?
>> Uh they go to go back to the secular
world to spread the message.
>> What message is this?
>> That God is love.
>> Okay.
>> But what happens to the people who don't
turn out to be big uh YouTubers who
talking about their near-death
experiences? Maybe they just pack up and
go on with their lives. Have you have
you been on YouTube? Have you looked at
how many Dear Dev Experience videos are
on YouTube? There's like millions of
them.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Millions of And there's way
more people who don't talk about it.
>> Um,
okay.
Look, there's lot Okay. Why would you
want to talk about it?
>> Yeah.
I think because that's everybody's
question since like Shakespeare said
like no where no travelers return and
then you're like wait I'm their traveler
they return. Yeah. So I have the you
know I'm the chosen messenger or
something to tell people about what the
ultimate philosophical question like oh
where do we come from? Well the Bible
tells us that but well we're going to
heaven but nobody knows where it's like
so I can kind of be the messenger.
>> What is the main message all these
people with narrative experiences? What
do they tell others?
um that God is grace and God is love.
>> Death is not the end.
>> Yes. Okay. Don't fear death.
Don't
lose your fear of death, it is nothing.
It's only just another beginning.
Uh yes.
>> Does that mean that if you refuse to
die, you could technically live to live
forever?
>> What? [laughter]
saying,
>> "Wait, wait." Um, okay. All right. Okay.
Repeat that. Okay.
>> Wait, wait. Because you said that when
you die, people say that God asked them,
"Do you want to uh go to heaven or do
you want to go home?" And then if you
just always say go home, can you
technically live forever like that?
I think only in near death experiences
where you you you are like be between
this gap of whether you can be saved or
not by medical um intervention then God
asks you to pick but if you're like dead
dead like stone dead by car accident
then you're just you after that's
actually that's actually a huge gap
between like uh near death and death and
that's actually a huge gap. So how does
God determine this?
just have to trust them, right? No, like
what I mean like like if medical means
cannot save you like you're like stone
dead like super out of like if you're
squeezed by a rock and you're like your
brain shuttered right then there's no
way but if you are like kind of in a car
concuss car accident you have concussion
your brain's a bit shaken but not like
crashed then maybe you know you got a
choice. I'm saying that there's a
spectrum of there's a there's a spectrum
of things here and I don't know at which
point is the cut off point like there
are
>> I guess God knows so if you see God ask
you the question then you you you know
you have a choice but if not
>> uh yes uh I still have a question
because the physic keeps telling us that
nobody can die because we're just energy
right energy will be forever in the
universe but what if we don't feel fear
of death but what fear which level we
will be because after we die uh we have
to go to some some heaven somebody we go
to go to hell. So if in that case you we
don't care about death but we care about
in which level we will be in after death
uh after you know uh
>> okay so let me ask you this question
okay let's just say we lose our fear of
death how would you live your life if
you lost your fear of death what would
you do
>> you may want to do whatever you want
because if you don't fear of death you
can't
>> what would you do
>> suicide
What?
Explain the logic here. Why would you
why would you commit suicide if you if
you lose your fear of death?
>> I mean, you don't really care about
living anymore, so you might
>> Okay. Okay, that's a possibility. Like,
well, you know, like, well, fear of
death. Um, I don't like my life, so I'll
just kill myself. Yes.
Did
what would you No. No. Like imagine
this, okay? Use your love, use your use
your intuition, use your imagination.
What would you do if you completely lost
your fear of death? Uh yet you then you
>> well that that's expiration, right? That
means the time you have you don't have
any more time left. So if you have
infinite time, then you would
>> No, no, that's not what I said.
>> I said you lose your fear of death. I
didn't say you live forever. I said you
lose your fear of death.
>> Say you you don't have this sense don't
have this fear of death, then you would
procrastinate. there would be no
motivation to agit to generate.
>> Okay. So, so you so you
>> maybe live your life to the fullest
because now you don't fear uh too much
anymore and you want to live your life
to the best of your ability so that you
can get more better place in heaven.
>> What would you do?
Um maybe get closer to God I guess like
to to learn more about him so that you
know I can end up in a higher sphere of
heaven I guess.
>> Okay. You would you would go and learn
more right?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Yes.
>> Um I once met this guy. He told me he
had a near-death experience when he was
like 20 or in very young and then
afterward he felt that his life was on
um was was on more was on extra time. So
his life has already ended. He is on
extra time and this time is just been
gifted to him. So he he's now like I
think 80 something, but he spent his
whole life pursuing um sustainability
and working in NGO and not making any
money.
>> Yeah, that's what the majority of people
will do. May maybe not everyone, okay?
Maybe maybe some people will just kill
themselves, but the majority of people
will just live the life to the fullest.
We'll just do whatever you want to do
now. Okay? Because you're not afraid of
death anymore. You're like, I don't
care. I'm just going to I have free
will. I have free choice. Okay?
Uh yes.
>> So uh I think it's more of uh no one
else gets to tell me how to live my life
anymore. So the whole the whole thing of
the Catholic Church is that if you don't
let us tell you what to do with your
life, then you're going to hell and it's
going to be horrible. But uh not being
afraid of death anymore, not being
afraid of this Catholic hell anymore
means that you're free to do what you
want deep down.
>> Exactly. that that's why Donnie wrote
Divine Comedy to free people of the fear
of death because as you point out the
real power of the Catholic Church is
they make people afraid of death, right?
If you don't obey us, we'll send you to
to hell,
right? If you don't obey us, you won't
get into heaven. So the what what the
real purpose of divine comedy is to
expand your imagination
by uh liberating you from your fear of
death. And they and it does that by
providing an imaginative universe that
is complete, that is detailed, and which
is all loving. There's no fear in
heaven, right? These angels aren't meant
to scare you. Like in Ezekiel, they're
meant to scare you. Uh God is meant to
scare you. But in Divine Comedy, it's in
in heaven, it's all embracing. It's all
forgiving. It's all welcoming.
Does that make sense?
Okay. Any
questions?
Okay. So, um, as I pointed out, there's
a reason why we did Paradise first, and
it's to really understand
the cosmology of Dante, understand why
he's doing what he's doing.
But ultimately
um Darn is not working in a vacuum,
right? It's not like he can just present
this poetry and it'll be accepted
because in this time of history there's
a greater power than the Catholic Church
and it's Virgil.
Okay? You think it's the Catholic Church
that has all the power, but it's Virgil
the poet who has all the power because
as as we said what poetry does is that
it embeds itself into the collective
unconscious
and the language and the beauty shapes
the way you see the world. So Donny's
real conflict, his real enemy is not the
Catholic Church, it is Virgil. Okay. So
now what we'll do for the rest of this
um rest of our time together is explore
this cosmic conflict between Virgil and
Dante and not only that but we will
apply it to our world and see how this
conflict is shaping our world. Okay,
does that make sense? Okay, so now
uh we are done with paradise. We're
leaving paradise and we're going to go
to
hell. Okay. So this is counter one
inferno.
This is a great website, right? It's so
easy to navigate.
>> Yeah. Go ahead.
>> Does being in vegetative state um in
include as part of near-death
experiences? Because technically I know
a lot of people like once like people
can kind of like know what you're
thinking of their first thought is like
to kill me. But we literally just said
that if you're in near-death situation,
God will ask you whether you want to
live or not. So is this kind of like an
exception to this concept? Like I'm just
a little bit confused. I'm sorry.
>> Okay. So the idea is uh what happens if
you're in a coma? Well, if you're in a
coma, it's also very much like a
near-death experience. And again, God
asks you, do you want to live or not,
right? Because there are people who wake
up from a coma and there are people who
don't wake up from a coma. And I think a
lot of it has to do with your will to
live. Okay? Does that make sense?
Okay. All right. So, this is counter one
of inferno. Okay.
All right. Um,
the very beginning.
>> Okay.
When I had journeyied half of my our
lives way, I found myself within a
shadowed forest. For I had lost the path
that does not stray. Ah, it is hard to
speak of what it was, that savage
forest, dense and difficult, which even
in recall renews my fear, so bitter
death is hardly more severe. But to
retell the good discovered there, I'll
also tell the other things I saw. I
cannot clearly say how I had entered the
wood. I was so full of sleep just at the
point where I abandoned the true path.
But when I'd reached the bottom of a
hill, it rose along the boundary of the
valley that had harassed my heart with
so much fear. I looked on high and saw
its shoulders clothed already by the
rays of that same planet which serves to
lead men straight along all roads. At
this my fear was somewhat quieted. For
through the night of sorrow I had spent
the lake within my heartfelt terror
present. And just as he who with
exhausted breath having escaped from sea
to shore, turns back to watch the
dangerous waters he has quit, so did my
spirit, still a fugitive, turn back to
look intently at the past that never has
let any man survive.
I let my tired body rest a while. moving
again. I tried the lonely slope. My firm
foot always was the one below. And
almost where the hillside starts to
rise, look there, a leopard, very quick
in life. A leopard covered with a
spotted hide. He did not disappear from
sight, but stayed. Indeed, he so impeded
my ascent that I had often to turn back
again. The time was the beginning of the
morning. The sun was rising now in
fellowship with the same stars that had
escorted it when divine love first moved
those things of beauty. So that the hour
and the gentle season gave me good cause
for hopefulness hopefulness on seeing
the beast before me with his speckled
skin. But hope was hardly able to
prevent the fear I felt when I beheld a
lion. His head his head held high and
ravenous with hunger. Even the air
around him seemed to shudder. This lion
seemed to make his way against me. And
then as she woof showed herself, she
seemed to carry every craving in her
leanness. She had already brought
despair to many. The very sight of hers
waited me with fearfulness that I banded
hope of ever climbing up that mountain
slope. Even as he who glories while he
gains will when the time has come to
tally laws. Lament with every thought
and turn despondent. So was I when I
faced that restless beast which even has
he she stopped me step by step had
thrust me back to where the sun is
speechless. While I retreated down to
lower ground before my eyes there
suddenly appeared one who seemed faint
because of the long silence. When I saw
him in that vast wilderness, have pity
on me were the words I cried. Whatever
you may be, a shade a man. He answered
me, not man. I once was man. Both of my
parents came from Lombardi and both
claimed Manua as native city. And I was
born though late S Julio and lived in
Rome under the good Augustus, the season
of the false and lying gods. I was a
poet and I sang the righteous son of
Ankases who had come from Jo Troy when
flames destroyed the pride of Ilia.
And why do you return to wretchedness?
Why not climb up the mountain of
delight, the origin and cause of every
joy?
And are you then that vigil? You the
fountain that really pours so rich a
stream of speech. I answered him with
shame upon my brow. a light and honor of
all other poets. May my long study and
the intense love that made me search
your volume serve me now. You are my
master and my author. You the only one
from whom my writing drew the noble
style from which I have been honored.
You see the beast that made me turn
aside. Help me, oh famous sage, to stand
against her, for she has made my blood
and pulses shudder. It is another path
that you must take, he answered when he
saw my cheerfulness. If you would leave
the savage wilderness, the beast that is
the cause of your outcry allows no man
to pass along her track, but blocks him
even to the point of death. Her nature
is so squalid, so malicious that she can
never sate her greedy will. When she has
fed, she's hungrier than ever. She mates
with many living souls and shall yet
mate with many more until the greyhound
arrives inflicting painful death on her.
That hound will never feed on land or
pewtor, but find his fair and wisdom,
love, and virtue. His place of birth
shall be between two felts. He will
restore low-lying Italy for which the
maid Camila died of wounds and nus and
Urealis.
and he will hunt that beast through
every city until he thrusts her back to
hell, for which she was first sent above
by envy. Therefore, I think and judge it
best for you to follow me, and I shall
guide you, taking you from this place
through an internal place, where you
shall hear the house of desperation and
see the ancient spirits in their pain,
as each of them laments his second
death. And you shall see these souls who
are content within the fire, for they
hope to reach whenever that may be the
blessed people. If you would then ascend
as high as these, a soul more worthy
than I am, will guide you. I'll leave
you in her care when I depart.
Because that emperor who reigns above,
since I have been rebellious to his law,
will not allow me entry to his city. He
governs everywhere but rules from there.
There is his city, his high capital. Oh
happy those he chooses to be there. And
I replied, "Oh poet, by that God whom
you had never come to know, I beg you
that I may flee this evil and worse
evils to lead me to the place of which
you spoke, that I may see the gateway of
St. Peter and those whom you describe as
sorrowful." Then he set out and I moved
on behind him.
>> Okay, so this is the very beginning of
Divine Comedy. And again, we've been in
paradise. So, we know exactly what this
cosmology is. Um, this is year 1300 and
Donna is like the middle age, right? So,
35 or 40. And he is in a shadow forest
and he has absolutely no idea where he's
going. Okay? So, he's basically in a
midlife crisis.
And when he walks around, he sees these
beasts,
right? and these beasts block his way
forward
and he's looking for escape. And so
Virgil shows up and says, "Let me guide
you." And then Donnie is like, "You're
my hero. You're you are the person who
I've worshiped all my life and
um how can we bypass these beasts?" Uh,
yes.
>> I have a question which is why is Dante
being so modest right now?
>> Being so what?
>> Modest.
>> Being so modest.
Okay.
That's because he's lost.
He's scared.
He's hungry. If someone's gonna come and
give you some food, you you better be
modest, right?
Right.
But also,
um, does Dante
respect Virgil?
Yeah, a lot. Right. Because at this time
in history, if you are, um, an educated
person, you all read Virgil. And how do
you read Virgil? Do you guys know?
No. But like like like how do you study
Virgil?
You have to memorize Virgil. Okay? Like
like you don't actually sit down and
analyze Virgil. You just memorize it
word for word. And that's just how you
learn Latin. And if you were educated,
you had to speak Latin the way that
Virgil spoke Latin. That's how you prove
your eloquence. Okay? So Dante is in awe
of Virgil. Dante sees Virgil as a father
figure. Does that make sense? So you
have to appreciate that at this time in
history
uh Dante is worships Virgil and Virgil
is going to be his guide. Okay. So so
let's let's continue the story where
Virgil shows up and Don is like how do
we get past the beast and Virgil says
you can't get past through the beast.
You have to go through another way. You
have to go through hell.
Okay. So c can someone explain to me
what this is a metaphor for?
First of all, why is Dante in the
forest? Why is he lost? And what do the
bees represent? And why does St. Virgil
says you can actually you cannot
actually defeat the bees. You cannot
actually confront the bees. You just
have to avoid the beast.
What is this a metaphor for? Yes. Uh
actually I think beast is just kind of
anger, fear or some kind of you know
which is not so good character in his
mind. And the fur is it means that he
just get lost so he just be exiled you
know.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Exactly. That's that's
exactly correct. Right. Where he is
middle-aged and his life sucked. His
life is falling apart. Uh he's been
exiled from he's about to be exiled from
Florence. His political faction. Uh the
white gels are in conflict and losing to
the black wealth. Okay. So he's
completely lost as like how did they get
to this point? I see no possible path
forward. And he is consumed by anger, by
hatred, by fear. And that confuses you.
That that blinds you from seeing any
possible path. And what Virgil was
saying to him is like you cannot
actually confront your anger. You can't
confront your hatred. You can't confront
your fear. The only thing you can do is
learn more,
open your mind,
develop your imagination, and then these
beasts will naturally go away. Does that
make sense, guys? Never ever try to
confront your anger. Uh never try to
confront your fear, your doubts. That
doesn't get you anywhere.
Develop more experiences. Right?
So,
let's just say that uh you have problems
with your parents, okay? You really
really hate your parents. You go to a
therapist
and your therapist tells you, "Well, we
need to talk talk to you about your
parents, okay? So, talk about all these
memories you have as your
uh as a child, right? And we will
through talk therapy
uh reimagine your childhood." Okay? Is
that a good idea? Would I agree to to to
to this?
Why why not? What why not? What's the
problem with that?
Uh because I'll be like just uh like the
metaphor like facing the beast and
uh I don't think like by
by confronting with your anger you can
like uh like you can find like a
resolution through throughout that.
>> That's what D says. But why? What
happens when you confront the beast?
>> Uh, yes.
>> You get more tangled up in it, you get
more angry, relieving or remembering.
>> You feed the beast, right?
>> When you confront the bees, you feed the
bees. So, the more you talk about how
angry you are, you become more angry.
So, what's the solution? Okay. Like, you
know, you're like, you know, you're
you're you don't really don't like your
parents. It's bothering you.
And so
how can you get over this?
>> So you go out and have life experiences
yourself. You go out, fall in love,
become a parent yourself, and then your
parents.
>> Exly. Okay. Exactly. Okay. Okay. That's
the better path. And and and that's what
Virgil was saying like let's not do talk
therapy. Let's not go to therapy, guys,
because because all that's going to do
is feed the beast. It'll just make you
more trapped in this pores. Let us go
through hell. And then if you see what
anger, fear, and hatred does to people,
this will help you elevate or or help
you aliate reduce your anger, fear. Uh
yes.
>> Um to me it seems a lot like you're it
seems like uh what they're suggesting is
more like ignoring stuff and distracting
yourself from stuff rather than
confronting stuff.
>> Okay. What? What's the response? It
seems like Don is running away, right?
What What's the response?
Anyone?
Yeah. Yeah.
>> Well, I mean, that's the point of what
he's saying. It's not to confront. It's
to find a new way.
>> Yeah. You don't have to confront
something to defeat something. Okay. You
can go around that that thing. Why do
you need to to run into a wall? Why
can't just walk around the wall? Yeah.
>> Yeah. It's kind of like the Chinese
wisdom, I guess. It's like you kind of
go around it. You don't have to go
straight to show that you defeated it or
confront it directly. You can still
solve the problem in many different
ways, right? What I'm trying to say is
that yeah, you can go around it and you
can ignore it and for the time being and
that's going to be way better than if
you do talk therapy, if you dive deep
down into it. But the point is that it's
still there and it might ambush you
every single day. Like when you're
angry, truly angry about something, it
might ambush you every single day and it
might ruin everything else. So why not
confront it?
>> You are confronting it by going to hell
already. So you're still taking an
active action to get rid of it by going
to hell. So you solve it. It won't
ambush you anymore.
>> And so just going to hell solves me all
my problems. Like I take Yeah. Like I
take a round trip to hell and it solves
the problems. Uh yes. Uh maybe because
you know uh all of this anger fear it
cannot be distinguished. It cannot be
destroyed. It just always may exist in
your mind. So the better way you just
not just to kill them or or unless you
kill yourself, right? So you had better
to avoid it maybe.
>> Okay. Yeah.
>> So something I struggled with personally
is we just finished the paradisio and so
he was a was arrogant and enlightened
person there and It's struggling for me
to then go back to the Inferno where
he's a flawed, sinful person without all
the answers and he's got to go through
the next three books to get most of the
answers. So maybe he is making some
mistakes. Maybe he's not perfect right
this moment.
>> Yeah.
Right. Okay. So he has to go through
this journey if he's if he's descend
to find his true self. Okay. All right.
Uh, let's keep on reading.
KTO 2.
The day was now departing. The dark air
released the living beings of the earth
from work and weariness. And I myself
alone prepared to undergo the battle
both of the journeying and of the pity.
Which memory mistaken not shall show. Oh
muses, oh high genius, help me now. Oh
memory that set down what I saw. Here
shall your excellence reveal itself. I
started. Poet, you who are my guides,
see if the force in me is strong enough
before you let me face that rugged past.
You say that he who fathered Sylvius,
while he was still corruptible, had
journeyed into the deathless world with
his live body. For if the enemy of every
evil was courteous to him, considering
all he would cause and who and what he
was, that does not seem
incomprehensible, since in the imperion
heaven he was chosen to father honored
Rome and her empire. And if the truth be
told, Rome and her realm were destined
to become the sacred place, the seat of
the successor of great Peter. And
through the journey you ascribed to him,
he came to learn of things that were to
bring his victory into the papal mantle.
Later, the chosen vessel traveled there
to bring us back assurance of that faith
with which the way to our salvation
starts. But why should I go there? Who
sanctions it? For I'm not Anas. I'm not
Paul, nor I, nor others. myself so
worthy.
>> Okay. So again, um he's being really
really modest here, right? He's saying
um
Virgil says like we have to go into hell
and uh Don is saying it's like I'm not
worthy at all because you think of all
these major figures who's been to hell.
Um
I'm not worth worthy, right? Because who
who's who's been to hell?
You have Inas who's the hero of the uh
Iniad. You have Paul. And who else do
you have?
>> Jesus went to hell.
>> Jesus. Yes. The chosen vessel. Jesus
been has been to hell. Okay. So, it's
almost like a special privilege where
you don't die, but you still still go to
hell. It's a It's only if you're a
really really special person would you
have that access. Okay. Uh, so God is
like, "I'm not worthy, Virgil. I can't
go into hell." And uh, keep on going.
>> Verse 34.
Therefore, if I consent to start this
journey, I fear my venture may be wild
and empty. You're wise. You know far
more than what I say. And just as he who
unwills what he wills and shifts what he
intends to seek new end so that he's
drawn from what he had begun, so was I
in the midst of that dark land, because
with all my thinking I anold the task I
had so quickly undertaken. If I have
understood what you have said, replied
the shade of that great-hearted one.
Your soul has been assailed by cowardice
which often weigh so heavily on a man
distracting him from honorable trials as
phantoms frighten beasts when shadows
fall that you may be delivered from this
fear. I'll tell you why I came and what
I heard when I first felt compassion for
your pain.
>> Okay. So do you understand like Donnie
right now in his middle age he is lost
in the forest because of his fear. Okay.
He has been seized by fear. Um uh Give
away.
>> Verse 52. I was among those souls who
are suspended. A lady called to me so
blessed, so lovely that I implored to
serve at her command. Her eyes surpassed
the splendor of the stars. And she began
to speak to me so gently and softly with
angelic voice. She said, "Oh spirit of
the courteous manuan, whose fame is
still a presence in the world and shall
endure as long as the world lasts. My
friend who has not been the friend of
fortune is hindered in his path along
that lonely hillside. He has been turned
aside by terror. From all that I have
heard of him in heaven, he is I fear
already so astray that I have to come to
help him much too late. Go now with your
persuasive word, with all that is
required. see that he escapes. Bring
help to him that I may be consoled. For
I am Beatatrice who sends you on. I come
from where I most long to return. Love
prompted me. That love which makes me
speak. When once again I stand before my
lord. Then I shall often let him hear
your praises. Now Beatatrice was silent.
I began.
>> Okay. Stop. Okay. All right. So Virgil
is telling Dante how Virgil came to him.
Right. So Dante is lost in the forest
and Beatric up in heaven hears Dante's
pain, fear, agony. And Beatrice
uh with permission from God ascends to
hell where Virgil is and says, "Virgil,
please help my friend Dante. You help my
friend Dante, God will give you a
special consideration." Okay.
Why is Dante being helped by God?
Why would God care?
Yes.
>> Because Beatatrice wants him to be
helped and to lift him out of hell.
>> Okay. So, so let's think about
[clears throat] this. Okay. All right.
Um, so
why
would God
care
about Dante?
>> Wants him to write. He wants him to be a
poet and write record see and record all
these things.
>> And how would God know that Dante
is a chosen one?
Like there's a lot of people in the
world. Why Dante? Yes.
>> Because of his love for Beatrice.
>> Yes. Okay. Do you understand the logic
of this? Okay.
Regardless of Dante's fear, anger, and
hatred, regardless of the fact that he's
lost in the forest, he still
has this passion for Beatatrice that has
allowed Beatric to ascend to heaven.
Okay. God's like, "Hey, Beatric, what
are you doing here?" And is like, "Well,
D loves me a lot, so I'm here." And and
then God's like, "Wait, wait, who is
this Donnie guy?" Right? So Donnie is
special because he for his poetry is
able to elevate Beatric to heaven. And
now that Dante is lost in the woods,
um Beatric will now reciprocate, right?
Says, "Well, you know, you you are the
special person who put me here. You're
lost."
And so we're going to help you find your
way because your true mission is to
ascend to heaven and write the divine
comedy. Okay. Does that make sense?
Okay. All right. But you appreciate why
I I had to teach paradise first, right?
Because if I had to if I if I taught
this taught this first, we'd just be
confused. Okay. But now that we know
what the ending is, we can go back and
see how it was constructed. But another
way of saying this is like think of
think about the year 1300. You didn't
have a computer,
right? How you how you able to do that?
Can see the entire thing in its totality
even before you wrote anything down,
right? You saw you see how the beginning
connects so well to the ending. Does it
make sense? Like how are you going to do
this? It's like basically um
um you know being being able to write
the entire TV series, all 10 seasons,
um, even before you begin to write
episode one. Uh, yes.
>> Do we know for sure Dante wrote the
Inferno first?
>> Yes. Yes. Because he published Inferno
first. Yes. Right. So, so, so, um, he
had patrons and he would write these
manuscript forms for his patrons. So, he
first published the Inferno, then
published Purgatory, then published uh,
Paradiso. But like what is shocking is
that there are no inconsistencies.
Do you understand? There are actually no
inconsistencies between the paradise and
in between inferno. How is he able to do
this?
Does anyone know? I mean he has to have
a preconception.
Either it's divine or he has to have a
preconception of the structure that he's
going to use for all of this. Right.
>> Right. But but I'm saying like how he's
able to do this, right? Do you guys
know?
Okay. So, um let me explain how how he's
able to do this. And again, I'm not him.
I don't know. Okay.
But for Dante, the world of
um infernal, purgatory, and paradiso
are real worlds with real people. Does
that make sense?
They're more real to him than his own
world. And so when he traveled in these
world, he was meeting these people. And
these people were separate from him and
they were real people. So he was
actually meeting Virgil and talking to
Virgil. And Virgil was talking to him
not as a figment of Donny's imagination,
but as Virgil, the real person who wrote
the inad.
Does that make sense?
Okay. He's like, there's no other way to
do this. How else could you construct
something so vast, so complete, and so
consistent, so coherent, unless it was a
real world to you? And you wonder this
world meeting real people with real
psychology, real motivations.
Does that make sense?
All right, let's keep on going.
>> Verse 76.
>> And and again again like we have already
read paradise so we know exactly what
happens. So we can spot any
inconsistencies right in inferno and I'm
telling you right now there is none
there absolutely no inconsistencies
in
um the um in in any of the divine comedy
and again if you if you if you are able
to use your imagination you can resell
everything within it it's all logically
coherent and consistent. This is pretty
amazing. Okay, because you can't do that
actually do this with any other text.
Actually, sorry, Homer, you you do this
with homework. Okay, keep on going.
>> Line 76. Oh, Lady of Virtue, the sole
reason why the human race surpasses all
that lies beneath the heaven with the
smallest spheres. So, welcome is your
wish that even if it were already done,
it would seem tardy. All you need to do
is let me know your will. But tell me
why you have not been more prudent,
descending to the center, moving from
that spacious place where you long to
return.
Because you want to fathom things so
deeply, and I I now shall tell you
promptly, she replied, "Why, I'm not
afraid to enter here. One ought to be
afraid of nothing other than things
possessed of power to do us harm. But
things inocuous need not be feared. God
and his graciousness have made me so
that this your misery cannot touch me. I
can withstand the fires flaming here. In
heaven, there's a gentle lady, one who
weeps for the distress toward which I
send you, so that stern judgment up
above is shattered. And it was she who
called upon Lucia, requesting of her,
now your faithful one has need of you,
and I commend him to you." Lucia, enemy
of every cruelty, arose and made her way
to where I was, sitting beside the
venerable Rachel.
>> Again, remember, okay, we've been in
paradise. You know exactly where where
Beatric is, right? Beatric is sitting
next to Rachel and it says it here as
well. Okay, there's actually no
inconsistency in Divine Comedy. Uh, keep
on going.
Verse 103. She said, "You beat true
praise of God. Why have you not helped
him who loves you so that for your sake
he's left the vulgar crowd? Do you not
hear the anguish in his cry? Do you not
see the death he wars against upon that
river ruthless as the sea? No one within
this world has ever been so quick to
seek as good or flee as harm as I. When
she had finished speaking thus to come
below.
>> Why doesn't Beatus know about Donnie's
agony?
Why?
So Donnie is in agony and someone else
um had to tell Beatatrice.
But why didn't Beatrice know for
herself? They're all up in heaven. They
can say everything together. Why didn't
Beatric
know for herself? Why does someone have
to tell her
Dante is in pain? He's in pure agony. He
he's he is u he has become overwhelmed
with fear, doubt, anger, hatred.
And Beatatrice is the last to know,
right? Even though they have this cosmic
divine connection together.
Why?
>> Because you love this person so much,
you don't want that person to know.
>> Exactly. Okay. You understand? It's
because Donnie loves her so
much. He
does not want her to know he is in pain.
Okay. Again, the consistency here,
right?
Think about how consistent this is.
All right. Uh let's keep on going.
Line 112. To come below down from my
blessed station, I trusted in your
honest utterance, which honors you and
those who have listened to you. When she
had finished with her words to me, she
turned aside her gleaming, tearful eyes,
which only made me hurry all the more.
And just as she had wished, I came to
you. I snatched you from the path of the
fierce beast that barred the shortest
way up the fair mountain. What is it
then? Why? Why do you resist? Why does
your heart host so much cowardice? Where
are your daring and your openness as
long as there are three such blessed
women concerned for you within the court
of heaven? And my words promise you so
great a good as little flowers which the
chill of night has bent and huddled.
When the white sun strikes grow straight
and open fully on their stems, so did I,
too, with my exhausted force. And such
warm daring rushed into my heart that I,
as one who has been freed again, began.
Oh, she compassionate who has helped me,
and you who courteous obeyed so quickly
the true words that she had addressed to
you. You, with your words, have so
disposed my heart to longing for this
journey. I returned to what I was at
first prepared to do. Now go. A single
will fills both of us. You're my guide,
my governor, my master. These were my
words to him. When he advanced, I
entered on this steep and savage path.
>> Okay. So, uh to summarize, Dante is
lost. He's afraid and he's confused and
he doubts everything. Right? So Virgil
comes to him and says, "Dante, let us I
will guide you forward." And Dante is so
consumed with fear that he does
everyone. He says, "Virgil,
um, I don't really belong in hell. I
really don't believe we can journey this
way." And Virgil says, "I see your fear.
I see your doubt. But let me assure you
that the person who who is really
helping you is not me, but Beatatrice."
at at the mention of the name
Beatatrice, Dante is able to fully trust
Virgil now and fully trust himself.
Okay.
So uh not not so by um helping Beatric
ascend to heaven basically Dante has
imagined his own salvation
right okay so that's it uh for today or
any questions about today
yes
why did Virgil agree to Oh, uh, Dante.
What? What does Virgil say?
>> Virgil said, um, Beatatric sent him.
>> No, no, but I'm saying what? What? Why
did Virgil What did Virgil tell Dante?
Did Did you guys dance? Remember,
it's actually why why most guys do do
stuff, by the way. Yeah.
>> Like the three ladies asked the Virgil
to help. Not the three ladies, one lady.
Right. Is it's actually the reason why
most guys do stuff in life. Okay.
Seriously.
Right. Why? Why? Why?
>> God will reconsider to put him.
>> No. No. It's [clears throat] not like
guys do stuff in life. Okay. Why?
>> Some ladies asked them to do
>> some beautiful lady asked her to go do
it, right? Do you understand? It's
because it's beautiful. She's like, "Ah,
she's really hot. I I'll go do it." It's
really that simple. Okay. Don't
overthink guys, right? Men are men are
not that complicated.
If a beautiful woman comes to me and
says, "Hey, I need to go do something."
I'll go do it. I I don't care what it
is.
Right.
Is this a re revelation to you? Did you
not know this before?
>> Just didn't expect it to be this.
>> Okay. So the divine comedy the what the
reason why it's so powerful and the
reason why it's lasted even to today is
its truth and beauty right because it's
able to resonate with you because the
people inside the divine company are
real people
right motivations his psychology it is
what a real person would do a real guy a
really hot lady said go help my friend
the guy would go do it okay he's not
think oh well maybe maybe I should give
me a million bucks or maybe oh hey maybe
you know she'll get me in heaven. He
doesn't care. Okay.
All right. So again, uh this is a
remarkable achievement. And by the this
year 1300, right? So this is before Mar
psychology,
right? This is before we know so much
about human emotions. Uh yes.
>> On top of um the reason why we started
with paradisial on top of the structure,
are there any other reasons that you
started with paradisial?
>> Yeah. So the main reason is that and
this is like really hard for people to
appreciate because they only read the
Inferno but Virgil is an unreliable
narrator. Do you understand? So
everything that Virgil tells Dante is
not true and it's really strange and
this is this is why um people don't
really understand Divine Comedy because
they take Virgil's words as Dante's
words and it's not true. If you read
Paradiso and you hear what Virgil says
about God, about uh hell, about love,
it's all in contradiction with paradise.
Okay? Do you understand?
And like once you understand that, then
you understand what what's really
motivating Dante. Dante's real mission
is to displace Virgil as the poet of the
universe and replace him with his
poetry. Okay? Does that make sense?
That's what his real mission is. That's
what the real battle is.
>> Is is Dante in his puris form whereas uh
uh inferno starting from inferno he's
kind of learning how he wants to write
the divine call or rather it's the
beginning of his connection.
>> No. So so what what Donnie believes is
the road to truth you must first pass
through untruth. You understand? You
must learn what's wrong and figure out
why it's wrong for yourself before you
can actually access the truth. That's
why you have to go through hell, right?
In hell, everything's going to lie to
you and everything you believe is going
to be wrong. But then you through
purgatory, you slowly begin to reveal
the truth to yourself, okay? But you
have to pass through that path of
miseducation in order to receive
education. You must embrace the lie
before you can actually seek the truth.
Okay?
So, so again um um something that that
you will notice is that what Virgil will
say throughout the inferno is completely
contradictory to what we will know in
paradise. Okay? And unfortunately again
uh the way that divine comedy is taught
is wrong. You're just taught inferno and
that's it. Without actually knowing and
fully experiencing this journey from
infernal to paradise, you can't actually
appreciate Donny's message. All right.
Okay. So that's it for today. I will see
you guys tomorrow. Okay? And please,
please review everything that we've
learned just so that you can test what
I've been teaching. Okay? Make sure that
what I've been teaching conforms to
actual text. And if it doesn't, then
bring this up, okay? Because because
then you'll be helping me learn as well.
All right? Okay. I'll see you guys
tomorrow.